<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Our Lordes famile and many other poinctes depending upon it opened against a Iew, Rabbi David Farar: who disputed many houres, with hope to overthrow the gospel, opened in Ebrew explication of Christianitie; that instructed, Rabbi Abraham Ruben. With a Greke epistle to the Geneveans. By H. Broughton.</title>
            <author>Broughton, Hugh, 1549-1612.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73571</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123739</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900398</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900398</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152051</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73571)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152051)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2003:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Our Lordes famile and many other poinctes depending upon it opened against a Iew, Rabbi David Farar: who disputed many houres, with hope to overthrow the gospel, opened in Ebrew explication of Christianitie; that instructed, Rabbi Abraham Ruben. With a Greke epistle to the Geneveans. By H. Broughton.</title>
                  <author>Broughton, Hugh, 1549-1612.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[98] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yere 1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: pi⁴ (.)⁴ A-K⁴ L²  chi¹.</note>
                  <note>With an unsigned leaf of errata at end.</note>
                  <note>Signatures K-L are in Greek.</note>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1475-1640 reel 2003 lacks leaves K3 and K4.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christianity and other religions --  Judaism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Judaism --  Relations --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152051:1"/>
            <p>OVR LORDES FAMILE AND MANY OTHER POINCTES <hi>DEPENDING VPON IT:</hi> opened againſt a Iew, Rabbi David Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rar: who diſputed many houres, with hope to overthrow the Goſpel, opened in Ebrew explication of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie; <hi>That inſtructed, Rabbi Abraham Ruben.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a Greke Epiſtle to the Geneveans.</p>
            <p>By H. Broughton.</p>
            <p>Printed at Amſterdam in the yere 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:152051:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152051:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:152051:3"/>
            <head>A Table of the chief pointes handled in this booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of our Lordes familie</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Iudahs Kindomes perſones.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of a vvicked Table.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Machmads Keys of Paradiſe:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of D. Bilſons profe, that our L. vvent hence to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Athanaſius miſtaken by the B.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of his three Syllogiſmes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Catachthonia: that it meaneth not Hell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Hades, that it neuer ſignifieth Hell in the N. Teſtament.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Gregorie Nazianzen for Tartaros.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of a Ievvs diſputation againſt the goſpell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For Scripture text.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Daniels ending Moyſes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the Iudaiſme of M. Livelie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of vvarrant to tranſlate Ebrevv:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the fourth Kingdome in Daniel: that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes are not meant in it.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152051:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TOT THE KINGES MAIESTIE. Cum tot ſuſtineas, &amp; tanta negotiaſolus in publica commoda peccem, Silongo ſermone morer tua tempora Caeſar.</head>
            <p>I Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſpeak to the King, as Horace to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus: and affect brevitie, which he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth mete for ſpech to a King. A Thracian Iew wrote from the City of our Conſtant in vnto the Land of his Mother, to have from that ſoile, his City ſpirituallie builded; I prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted his Epiſtle, and ſent aunſwer, that when the King of Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhould rule all the Ila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, I should convenientlie perfome Ebrew buil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding, having moſt ſad promeſs for meanes, to fill the world with bookes of our faith, in the Chananean tongue, when the King cam to the other Scepter. And though the Noble Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of whom M. Iames Melvin from him wrote aſſurance, delayed: I made all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew inſtrumentes, and vttered bookes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my charges, in Ebrew, Greke, and other to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues,
<pb facs="tcp:152051:4"/> unto 36000: to fill the world quick he with clear opening of matter miſtake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by we gave Iewes occaſion to reject the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; and wherby they much diſgraced us un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Machmad They were greued to ſee their hope of victorie gone. And one lew of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam made requeſt, that I wold in an ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolemne audience, aunſwer him one after none, to ſuch argumentes, as by which Iewes gathered, that our Goſpel, could not be of God. Diſputation was graunted: and he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted an afternone: vainlie hoping to prove, that Luke told not our Lordes kindred, that Salathiel could not be ſon to Iechonias, and to Neri. That Romanes were the jmage leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that Daniels Seavens did not plainly end Circumciſion; that our Crede and Goſpel, could not be reconciled: that our Greke Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament was not pure in text. Yf he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved any of theſe, wherin our ſide aſſented much vnto him: he had foiled the aunſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. To all theſe I aunſweared: and now print the tenour, for the vſe of the Kinges natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es.
<pb facs="tcp:152051:4"/> And j wold go foreward with Ebrew &amp; Grek writinges, to be turned by others into all Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope tongues, for the light of Chriſtendome, Yf the King doe think good to perform, that wherof M Iames<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Melvin vvrote extreme aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveration. And j hartely wish, &amp; humbly de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſire, ſo much to be performed: as the judge Eternal knoweth due in faith, and a meanes to lighten the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt from the Weſt. Liberalitie of a Prince ſone great without band in ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler occaſiones, wold find in this kind from God and man, greater approbation. The King may appoint pay of promeſs, from Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall revenues: and yf any Biſhop can open the Bible in Ebrew and Greke; and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le the Bishops erroures better then my ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, j wold gladly give him place: &amp; j am ſure he wilbe an honour to the Biſhops &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, over the world. But yf neither the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops can deale with the Eaſt in Ebrew and Greke: &amp; in ſtory &amp; Thalmudiques, cannot contrive both Teſtamentes into ſure nerves: the King will take order, that others doe it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties moſt humble, H. Broughton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152051:5"/>
            <head>TO <hi>THE MOST NOBLE PRINCE,</hi> MAVRICE Land-Grave of Haſſia.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEN I came to Marpurg (Moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince) your Doctour promotor layd among poſitiones of al faculties, this one against me:</hi> quidam autumat Deſcendere ad inferos in ſacro Symbolo, eſſe idem quod aſcendere ad coelos, quod nos non credimus. <hi>And they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quested me to dispute: vvher I shevved that, all dead, be inferi, all vvhoſe ſoules be in Heaven: &amp; euerie taking of a lourney is deſcendere by ſcripture ſpeach. And yf an horſe die: antiquitie held it enough to ſay, he vvas dead: but for men, they toke more in their mouth: as,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>is he dead &amp; gone to the dwellinges of Hades.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And all Heathen vvold expound our Symbolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of faith to meane as the Goſpel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that our Lord vve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the most happy lodge of the happy. Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152051:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>milliones in England think ſo: your tendered the truly learned D. Fortius thinketh ſo: &amp; ſince I ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the cauſe, the flour of Chriſtendome thinketh ſo: though the Cyclopes of Aetna vvold haue ſvva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovved me up in their Gehennean torment. The Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>natours yelded, and ſvvare a great oth, that they vvold teach the teachers, to uſe ſtrangers better. Novv a Ievv hath dealt openly against me: vvher in your Doctours take vvith him, againſt my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brevv bookes to your Highnes and to your Brother the Grave of Hanavv. You haue ſene both tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. I defend the Goſpel: Yf Papiſt or Caluiniſtes doe croſs, I vvil combat. Your Highnes may tell your Doctours of flight or fight. It is not vvell, that men teach, vvhat they haue not learned themſelues.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highnes most humble Hugh Broughton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152051:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE,</hi> The Lordes of his Majeſties <hi>moſt honorable Privey Counſell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Kinges Majeſty (right honorable) myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded a fauour to my poor studies, vvhich M. lames Melvin vvrote I should look for. Yf it pleaſe anie of your Lordships, to putt his highnes in mind, I hope it vvillbe ſone performed. And I vvold glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take one yeres paie, of that vvhich vvas purpoſed yerelie. Beſides, I am to requeſt your Lordships to conſider a Genevean injurie done to me for the Kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ſake: That, I have expreſſed in an Epiſtle vnto themſelves. Yf the King knevv the vvhole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, his Majeſtie vvold be readier to vveigh my da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger for his affaires: &amp; to further my paines, for the common good of Christendome.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships moſt humble: H. Broughton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:152051:6"/>
            <head>The family of Ieſus Chriſt after the <hi>flesh: who is God bleſsed for euer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>After that Koheleth or Eccleſiaſtes had ſhewed all thinges vnder the ſun to be vain, that men might look how the ſoule immortal might ſtand in judgement, &amp; find the ioy of the Kingdome promiſed to Dauid, I opened Ieremies Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, how therin the Iewes hope of happines in this world was buryed with the deſtruction of temple, city, Kindome. And the ſame yere that Ieremy firſt wrote his Lamentationes, the noble Daniel ſo beloved of God was captiued, to Babylon, to rule his captiuers, as Ioſeph to rule Egypt; who thence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riueth the Kingdomes that vexed the holy Iewes religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: how Chriſt had all theyr actiones as opened in a book before his judgement throne, &amp; made a riddance of them by the day that he was to com into the world. And joyneth vnto theyr vtter conſumption, his coming in the cloudes of heauen: &amp; aſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto the Everlaſting throne promiſed vnto Dauid. There the Romanes begin theyr dealinges; &amp; vvill rule over the King of heauen, till they crucified the God of glory: Wherfor they are pictured after the tenour of all Daniels fower in one; The Lion, the beare, the fourheaded Leopard, &amp; the fourth the ten-horned, giue them armes, to make one of them fower, a beaſte ten-horned, colored like a Leopard, footed, as a bear, and mouthed like a Lion Theyr tribute or taxe over the world fell out euen vvith the time that Chriſt the God of heauen came from the father into this vvorld. And Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el taught vpon Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels fall vvhen God vvold by his ovvne blood open an Eternall Kingdome to them that beleued in him: and vvhen God in Chriſt wold enter into the vvorke of the tabernacle, euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining 30 yeres in the fleſh. So the faithfull ſavv vvhen the ſon wold dvvell in our taberna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le; of Abrahams ſede; whoſe fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, knovven rightly of fevv, &amp; perverted by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>evves, vvith many queſtiones depending heron, I open to all Chriſtianes; &amp; firſt
<pb facs="tcp:152051:7"/> ſhevv at the Entrance the reaſon of ſeverall beginnige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the holy men that ſpell or ſpeak vnto vs of God come in the fleſh.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of S. Mathews beginning from <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The full purpoſe of S. Mathew concerning the Kingdome of the Iewes, I will handle at large in due place: Now the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Abraham made the beginnig may be touched only; 1. Abraham vvas the firſt man to whom Chriſt was promiſed in plain termes; that in his ſede all the families of the earth ſhould be bleſſed, So a beginning from him is fit for Iewes and heathen.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In that Eue had a promeſſ that Chriſt ſhould deſtroy the workes of Satan, who deſtroyed the vorld, &amp; Kild Adam, to be dead in ſin, &amp; to leaue this world; our Lord his juſtice and death, &amp; reſurrection &amp; aſcenſion &amp; reſtoring Adams ſoule to juſtice, &amp; the new world wherein juſtices dwelleth, all theſe poinctes are cloſly taught; But contemned by the blinded of Satan, who delite to be vnwittj, &amp; vvill not ſo much ſtrain theyr care, as to vnderſtand vvhat God ſpeaketh. Novv to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham matters vvere ſhevved playner, that the deſtroyer of Satans workes; ſhould come of him; &amp; after death ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued; &amp; figured by Melchiſedek; &amp; as Abraham &amp; Sara dead from ſtrength of generation yet by faith vvere quickened: and iuſtified by faith; So they ſhould be, vvho beleued in God that raiſeth Chriſt from the dead. For theſe cauſes the beginng of the Nevv T. is fitly taken from Abraham.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of S. Marc.</head>
               <p>S. Marc dravveth his entrance from the laſt prophet vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Iohn Babtiſt is foreſhevved: &amp; from Eſays comfort vpon ſpech of the fall of Babel. vvhich matter vvas plainly expounded fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:7"/> time, vvhen Cyrus deſtroyed Babel. &amp; Marc his Goſpell is of half a ſeauen; to shevv Chriſt his teaching of the covenant for many. And as God vvold haue S. Mark to fortify the Angels Chronicle for the time: So he vvould haue the other thre E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſtes to haſten to the ſame. As S. Mathevv doth, vvhen he told that our Lord dvvelt in Narazet; as in the volume of the prophetes Eſ. xj he is called Nazer; &amp; in the Babylon Thal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mud in Chelek; Nazor is the name of the ſon of Dauid; Preſently after Thalmadique handling of that his name, he co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the Angel Gabrieis half ſeauen; &amp; ſo doth S. Luke, &amp; S. Iohn haſten to the preaching of Malachj the ſonne of Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charj. Wherby any might marveile hovv the Ievves could miſſe to receaue the King of glory coming to his ovvne hovvſ. And thus all the four evangeliſtes shevved care to fottifie that part. And God vvold haue it famous, turning it into a prover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be; for afflictiones conformable to the afflictiones of Chriſt; by all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to that time; That the afflictiones for Chriſt should be called the afflictiones of dayes 1260. or, of a time tvvo times &amp; half a time; &amp; monethes forty tvvo. So by alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones our Gracious Lord teacheth vs to mark the four evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſtes, for the half ſeauen of our Lordes preaching; &amp; ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally S. Mark; &amp; to go back with him to Daniel. And our Lords ovvne tongue doth call vs to marke the time: in the Parable of the fig tree fruteles, hindering the Earth. Which ſpech may be gathered to be ſix monthes, before the curſed fig tree vvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered. As Bucholkerus maketh a goodly compariſon, of that Parable, &amp; of our Lordes half ſeauen. So our Lord calleth vs from Elias Baptiſt vnto Elias the Thisbite: hovv in his time heauen vvas shut three yeres &amp; ſix monethes; vvarning that ſynce the heauens vvere opened at his baptiſme, vntil his ſoule should returne from the croſſ to heauen, yeres should be three &amp; ſix monethes. Novv the gathering of Elias times in the firſt of the Kinges vvold require long labour; But vve may be ſure it vvas vvell knovven amonge the Thalmudignes; as S. Iames
<pb facs="tcp:152051:8"/> ſpeaking to the Thalmudique maner, ſayth, that Elias pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſtayd raine three yeres &amp; ſix monethes. Thus the time of our Lords preaching is ſvvetely compared vvith other Scriptures. &amp; vve may be ſure that our Lord ſpake the truth; &amp; ſeing ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord told, in Daniel ch. 7. &amp; 12. That Antiochus should cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the lavves &amp; offring<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a time tvvo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imes &amp; an half; He vvold haue his time for ſanctifying the temple to be as vvell Knovven; &amp; as vvell meaſured; ſeing the alluſion Ap. 12. of a time, tvvo times, &amp; half a time, is taken from his preaching.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>In what moneth S. Marke beginneth <hi>his ſtory: &amp; the reſt, the opening of the heauens by the ſecond Elias.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Becauſe our Lord was baptized, even beginnig thirty, &amp; to open the Kingdome, by teaching the covenant to many, three yeres &amp; ſix moneth: Seing his ſoules paſſage from the croſſe to the fathes is certen in the fiftenth of Niſan; So his birth &amp; Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme ſhould be in the ſeauenth moneth, Aethanim. Which vvas the firſt moneth, after the creation of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the moneth Ethanim <hi>or September.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It may ſomwhat help to mark old ſtory of Aethanim from 1. Kinges. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. All Iſrael aſſembled to the King Salomon, in the moneth Aethanim, in the feaſt, that is the ſeauenth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth; And the ſacrificers brought the Ark of the covenant of the Eternal, vnto his place; vnto the Dabyr; vnto the holy of holy; &amp; the Cherubim ſpred theyr vvinges over the place o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ark. This ſo Solemne ſhould haue antitypon awnſwearable in high matter. And what thing els can be, but that the moſt holy was manifeſt in his temple; &amp; the army of Angels ſpred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:8"/> theyr winges; to haue him honored at his coming then into the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The explication &amp; ſtory, of the <hi>moneth Aethanim.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The moſt Lerned Chaldy paraphaſt Ionatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeaketh thus: of Aethanim. <hi>It is the moneth of the ancient, &amp; they called it the firſt moneth, of feſtiuity. But now it is the ſeauen moneth.</hi> Thus Dauid Kimchj doth expound him. <hi>Aethanim or ſtrength is the month wherin they gathered the fructs &amp; encreaſe of the earth, to theyr houſes. For that cauſe it is called the feaſt of gathering frutes. So Aethanim meaneth ſtrength: &amp; fructes &amp; entreaſe of the earth be the life of a man. And ſome of our doctoures expound Aetha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim, the moneth in which the fathers were borne. The ſtay (Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanim) of the world; as the ſpech, Mich. 7. 2. Heare ye mounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies; &amp; ye ſtrong foundationes of the earth. Others call it Aetha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im from the ſtrength of the lawes that are geuen for this moneth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th feaſtes, &amp; lawes.</hi> So Ralbag ſayth. <hi>I think it called the moneth Athanim, for the feastes: the ſtrong, &amp; teaching iuſtice: which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re in this moneth.</hi> This for Ralbag. The firſt day had the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets; the tenth, expiation; the fiftenth the feaſt of tabernacles for eight dayes. And Ionathans wordes cited of me afore, be thus expounded of Camchj. <hi>Before the time that Iſrael came from Aegypt, Tiſri or Aethanim was the firſt moneth. For in Tiſri the world was made. And by reaſon that the Children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el came from Aegypt in Niſan, it became the head of monethes, &amp; Tiſri became the ſeauenth. For ſo the bleſsed God ſayd vnto them. This moneth shalbe vnto you the firſt of monethes. To you, by reaſon that to the reſt of the world it is not first: For Tiſri is the firſt.</hi> And this much for the moneth. So Iohn Baptiſt well might begin the firſt day; &amp; aſſemble vnto him much People fourtene day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: And our I ord come to him the fiftenth day; when they had lerned of the ſtronger then the Baptiſt, who wold baptize
<pb facs="tcp:152051:9"/> with the holy Ghoſt, &amp; with fyer. So the four Evangeliſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Celebrating the Baptiſme celebrat the birth which was the ſame day 29. full yeres. So as the firſt Adam &amp; the other to Noah came to the world that moneth, Chriſt ſhould come; &amp; that time was fitteſt for Caeſar to bid men reſort to theyr cities; &amp; moſt likely that shepheardes wold yet be abroad with theyr ship; &amp; fitteſt for men to go into a riuer naked to be Baptized. And by Daniels half ſeauen Iohn brought in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme; for heathen; as Dauid &amp; Salomon only Baptized proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes; Maimony in Aſure Bia, tract. 12 &amp; 13. And yf his war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant had not bene ſure, &amp; plain, from Daniel, none might haue com to him for Baptiſme. So our Lord begining a new yere of his age then, shewed the ſame time of moneth to haue geven vs his coming into the world. And the Rabbines in Middras Rabba conclude that Meſſias ſhalbe borne in Aethanim or Tiſrj; full of feaſtes to teach of him. And God appointed no feaſtes for the winter; becauſe of the vnſeaſonablenes of the weather. Chryſoſtome miſtaking Iohns fathers ſtory, thinking that he miniſtred not in june but in September, began to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace the ſtate of the Goſpell. Hence Turk &amp; Iew ſcoph: that we place the byrth where the conception ſhould be; and can yeld no reaſon of our Goſpels narrationes which we make moſt vnlikely to be true. And Arias Montanus helpes Chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoſtom; that Zacharie ſhould be high ſacrificer, Wheras all Iewes know that the Candelſtick, Table &amp; altar of incenſe were without &amp; dayly gone to by the ordinarie ſacrificers. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, four times made the begining of Daniels half ſeauen, might haue taught the Iewes a ſure note, what Elias Malachj ſpake off. Now the end of all the Evangeliſtes is in the firſt moneth, towardes leauing the Aegypt of this world at the Paſcha. And at Pentecoſt, after, the law vvas giuen to Moſes; when the fyerj lavv of the ſpirit vvas by Ieſus geuen. So the concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iohn, vvher men placed his birth; falleth to Midſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; &amp; birth to the ſpring Aequinoctial, and likevviſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception
<pb facs="tcp:152051:9"/> of Mary fell moſt fitly to mydvvinter, &amp; our Lordes coming into the vvorld, to the firſt moneth after the creation, &amp; his redemption, to the firſt moneth for redemption from Egypt; Theſe matters agree vvith Scripture &amp; plain reaſon. But novv the altering of the date vvold to much troble the vvorld. It may paſſ amongeſt vs; as fit for conſidering a time vvhen vvinter feaſtes, &amp; leaſure to heare the lavv read hindereth none vvorkes; &amp; according to the conception; very many Lerned men haue cleared the truth, of late; &amp; all are to blame that will folow an old errour here, that diſturbeth law &amp; Goſpell. Iewes &amp; Turkes look on: &amp; the iuſt iudge, who hath eyes pure, that they cannot behold euell, will kepe from his heauenly city all that practiſe lying.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of S. Lukes begining.</head>
               <p>S. Luke joyneth the end of the old teſtament to the begining of the New. A moſt heauenly worke. And here note the very names. Zacharj &amp; Malachj end the ſpech of God in the old Teſtament; &amp; Zacharj &amp; Malachj are in the firſt ſpech of the Angel Gabriel in the New. The Angel Gabriel; who did tell of Antiochus Epiphanes, for dayes 2300. &amp; Generally of Gods hand vpon the Graecianes: he, tels of the ſecond Elias; or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachj, vnto Zacharj; an holy man: &amp; of the birth of Chriſt, whom he him ſelf named Chriſt; Daniel 9. &amp; here the time muſt be conſidered. Euen when the Grecianes were rooted out from vnder the cope of heauen: &amp; had not the governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one city in the world; but at Romanes taxe, in Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el were vtterly conſumed; as the former all, the Graecianes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they vvere parted: &amp; the Medes with Perſianes, &amp; the Chaldeanes; when the laſt of all theſe were conſumed, then the Angel Gabriel cometh twiſe to tell the joy of the Kingdome of heauen; for Iohn Elias: &amp; for Chriſt the moſt holy. Thus ſo heuenly a ioyning of the old Teſtament to the New ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:152051:10"/> be celebrated of all that will kepe the commaundement of praiſing God with vnderſtanding. And all teachers be wicked that wilbe ſpending time to theyr hearers, &amp; them ſelues, in matters of this world, wher the hearers be ſo wiſe aſ they, and not ſtudy firſt the truth of theſe matters, ſo gracious &amp; full of ſalvation, &amp; after, teach them vnto the world. Biſhops that wold teach with dexteritie to make all in the the Kingdomes able yf they wold to teach all the world, ſhould never be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyed for theyr 200000 lib. per annum; But they ſhould be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted moſt reverend &amp; right reverend fathers; &amp; ſuch Papae as Athanaſuis, &amp; the like in Grecia. But ours muſt alter much before all the lerned nobility vvill think them ſo referend &amp; ſo learned, as ſome nobles be, &amp; lower gentry, that never came in Pulpit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of S. Iohn begining the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>S. Iohn the laſt beginneth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before the begining: from the Eternall, called the word of Thalmudiques infinitely through Moyſes, as Onkelos nere S. Iohn foloweth them: ſayng for, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hova ſayd, the word of Iehova ſayd. S. Paul ſayth they tempted Chriſt; vvher they tempted Iehovah. This vvas the main com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat vvith the Thalmudiques: &amp; Cerinthianes, &amp; other hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques. And matter required that myndes longe occupied in ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier matter, ſhould at the laſt be called to conſyder the Eternity, of the heyre of all, vvhich made the vvorld. And S. Luke ſone after mention of Elias Iohn baptiſt, handleth the humanitie of Ieſus Coriſt, vp to Adam: vvhom Satan overraught to bring darkenes vpon him ſelf, before the ſun euer left him in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; &amp; then ioyneth a nevv combat to the old ſerpent; thence vvill I ſhevv the familie of our Lord: &amp; cmment vpon it; &amp; S. Mathevv ſhall folovv, touching ſucceſſion to the Kingdom, &amp; other dependantes, all for inſtruction of Ievves, &amp; ſuch as vvold not lay a trap to Ievves, &amp; theyr ovvne deſtruction.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:152051:10"/>
            <head>THVS THE TEXT SPEAKETH <hi>Luke. 3. from. v.</hi> 23</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd Ieſus himſelf euen began to be of</hi>
               <note place="margin">The no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of all that are: for yeres 3927 The pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: to which Heathen be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantes.</note> 
               <hi>thirty yeres: being, Sonne, of Ioſeph, (as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought) of Eli, of Matthat, of Leui, of Melchi, of Ianna, of Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, of Mattathias, of Amos, of Naum, of Eſli, of Nagge, of Maath, of Matathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, of Semei, of Ioſeph, of Iuda, of Ioanna, of Rheſa, of Zorobabel, of Salathiel, of Neri, of Melchi, of Abdi, of Coſam, of Elmodam, of Er, of Ioſe, of Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ezer of Iorim, of Matthat, of Leui, of Symeon, of Iuda, of Ioſeph, of Ionan, of Eliacim, of Melea, of Mainan, of Mattatha, of Nathan, of Dauid, of Ieſſe, of Obed, of Booz, of Salmon, of Naaſſon, of Aminadab, of Aram, of Eſrom, of Phares, of Iuda, of Iacob, of Iſaac, of Abraham, of Thara, of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, of Saruch, of Ragau, of Phalec, of Eber, of Sala, of Cainan, of Arphaxad, of Sem, of Noe, of Lamech, of Mathuſala, of Enoch, of Iared, of Malaleel, of Caina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of Enos, of Seth, of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:11"/>1 Here Children ſhould begin firſt to rede: &amp; to compare the ſorowfull combat of Adam killed on his firſt day from life of ſoule made dead in ſin, with the glorious combat of our Lord reſiſting the old ſerpent; &amp; driving him to flight. Luke. ch. 4.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Mary the mother of our Lord is in name left out: but in matter conteyned. For the terme Sonne through all theſe hath relation to Ieſus, as in the Laſt: Sonne of God. They vſe ſmall judgment that hould Adam called the S. of God S. Luke in Satans ſpech ch. 4. ſayeth that Ieſus was meant by him, Son of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Ioſephs father who begate him was named Iacob Math. 1. But as all maried men haue tvvo fathers, ſo Ioſeph: Dauid had Ieſſai &amp; Saul; Ioſeph had Iacob natural, &amp; Ely in Lavv. yet by argument only, Ioſeph is Elyes S. not expreſly.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Ievves &amp; Gentiles, that cam not to the ſtory of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, ſhevving Chriſt to be the ſon of God, by the might that raiſed him, vvold haue made a ſcoff, to ſee the mother layd dovvne in the Genealogie. And ſo the holy Gh. pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vveakenes leaueth Mary for name, out: but in, by argument &amp; ſure collection; as thus: Ieſus, Mary Ely. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The vvhole number is diſpoſed in order fit for memori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ten to the flod; ending the old vvorld; ten to Abraham heyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the nevv vvorld<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> repeating him, tvviſe ſeauen of moſt God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers are to Dauid; Then his S. NATHAN, 1. Chr.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Beginneth a tvventy; vvho Liued priuate obſcure men vnder the Kinges of Salomons houſe: vntil the captiuity of Babylon. Tvvo Liued in the captiuity. Salathiel &amp; Zorobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel. He vvas governour vvhen the Ievves vvere ſent home by Cyrus; vpon the Angel Gabriel his Meſſage for redemption, &amp; ending of Moſes at 490 yeres. Rheſa beginneth, &amp; out Lord endeth a nevv tvventy. Heathen in Euſebius making a Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle by ages vvold make but 400 yeres of 20. The Olympiq folovvers that vvold make 590 yeres; to diſturbe Daniels<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:11"/> light to all the Bible, &amp; our Lordes houſe, ſhevved ſmal iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement; The tvventy from Rheſa to our L. vvill be heauenly Championes for ſalvation joyning vvith Daniel in their nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; to kepe men from feining moo yeres then God reckoned.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When Ievves refuſe the auctority of S. Luke; &amp; all the Nevve Teſtament, they ſhould be told that for ciuil recordes all nations vvold blame them. So for the 15 of Tiberius, vvhen Pilate vvas governour of Iudea, &amp; Herod Tetrarch of Galily, &amp; Philip his brother Tetrarch of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>turea, &amp; Trachonis, &amp; Lyſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias Tetrarch of Abylene, vvhen Annas &amp; Caiphas vvere high Sacrificers, for all thoſe, civil recordes ſtand, knovven to many nationes; &amp; one mans auctority is not conſidered in them. So for the familie of a King. Nationes nere Knevv it; &amp; Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus vvold examine the matter yf doubt had bene: &amp; Scribes S. Lukes foes had confuted him yf fault had bene; But none did; as none could. So vvhen S. Mathevv maketh Rachab wife to Salmon he ſpeaketh according to Iewes ciuil recordes vvell knovven. And ſo vvhen S. Paul Sayth he vvas an Ebrevv con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually by fathers &amp; mothers, he knevv that other of Gama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liels ſcholers could examin that. So vvhen he calleth Andro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus &amp; Iunias, &amp; Herodion his conſins, his Kinſemen, that vvere yet Phariſces, had reproved him yf he had lyed. So vvhen S. Luke Sodenly calleth Saul Paul, he had felt reprofe yf the matter had not bene vvel Knovven. As vvhen he telleth King Agrippa &amp; Feſtus, hovv he vvas ſpoken to by Ieſus our Lord: Saul, Saul, vvhy doſt thou perſecute me; Feſtus vvold not haue ſayd, to him; thou are mad Paul; too much lerning maketh thee mad: yf he had not knovven that he had tvvo names. So vvhen Iohaiada, the father of Zacharie the martyr is called B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rachias, by the like notation, S. Mathevv knevv him ſelf vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Zach: one man in 2. names Math. 27.</note> by many like examples; and vvhen Zacharie the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of the prophecie of Chriſt his exaltation; &amp; of the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iding vpon an aſſe, &amp; ſold for 30 ſicles, is called of him Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie the exalter of God, he had vvarrantes enough from old
<pb facs="tcp:152051:12"/> ages ſo to do. And for Genealogies knovven to heathen: Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Edoms ſtory for the Kinges of Seir that reigned ſuceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urs before he vvas King in Iſrael, vvas an ancient vvarrant to S. Luke. So vvhen S. Mathew maketh King Iechonias that died without iſſue, father in place of Kingdome to one of Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons brother Nathan in very far deſcent, he knew that other Ievves foes to the Goſpel vvho knevv the Kinges familie vvold herein mainteine him. So Hercules familie &amp; Sparta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Kinges; &amp; Macedonian; &amp; Cyrus the Perſian, &amp; his coſyns Kinges of Pontus, &amp; Seleucidae &amp; Lagidae, are famous in ſundry Graeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; &amp; none vvill deny any vvithout bringing better record: So Ievves ſhould be required to bring other families of Zoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel, yf they deſpiſe our Euangeliſtes: and vve ſhould not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to deny that, vvhich a Turk or any heathen vvold be aſhamed to deny.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The names of our Lordes Line are evident to be ſagely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; &amp; in more vviſe ſort, then ever any feigner could think vpon. Many are from the Patriarkes; Ioſeph cometh oftneſt to ſhevv hovv Iudah honored the old Ioſeph, vvho bare in his Beryll all tribes names: next Levi &amp; Symeon &amp; Iuda but once: But no name of inferior Patriark; no Ruben, no Iſachar, no Zabulon, no Beniamin: the houſe vvold kepe the dignity.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Some in notation haue ſingular great vſe, to ſhevv the ende of Salomons houſe; &amp; the hope of Nathan, to come i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lieu of it, as Melch-j the King is mine; Ner-j The light, Cand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le or King is mine. So they ſvvare; (2. ſam. 21. 17.) to Dauid; Thou ſhalt go no more to vvar: for thou ſhalt not put out the Ner, light, or Candel of Iſrael. The holy &amp; humble Dauid ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth God that name in his pſalme, 2. Sam. 22. 29. For thou Eternal art my candle; &amp; the Eternal vvill lighten my darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. So Ner-j beareth a name for the throne of Dauid; that ſhall continue for euer.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Melch-j the King is myne, this name tendeth to the ſame mark plainly &amp; properly ſhevving the belefe to Sophony.
<pb facs="tcp:152051:12"/> Dauid knevv from Moſes, &amp; by Spirit of prophecy, no leſſe then Moſes, that his houſe wold not be vpright with God. But one ſhould rule man, perfectly iuſt: ruling in the feare of God. 2 Sa. 23. There, the lerned chaldy Ionathan, thus expoundeth Dauids vvordes. The mighty of Iſrael promiſed to place me a King vvhich is Chriſt, vvho ſhall rule in the feare of God. But Salomons houſe vvold be in many very bad; &amp; as thornes to be thruſt avvay; &amp; to be brent in their place. Salomons brother Natha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, marked &amp; vvold not neglect the ſpech of Dauid, againſt Salomons houſe: &amp; the old Nathans prophecie concerninge the yonge Nathans Sonne; And the Ebrevv tongue ſhevveth in the names of Nathans poſterity, their hope &amp; expectation of great glory. Here Academiq ſtudies come far ſhort: beſtovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many yeres in humane vvorkes; &amp; takinge no time to the holy tongue; vvhich in the very names of ſtately perſonages conteyneth all the marrovv of the holy ſtory. An for ſo much to knovv the ſimple vvordes, for termes touching man, in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams tongue, one vveke vvith good direction vvold furniſh any ſage mind ſufficiently. And all ſhould geue ſo much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to our redemer, as to ſerch to the bottome, all that could be ſerched for his fathers after the fleſh. We may be ſure that all the ſage vviſdome that could be in names ſhould appeare in his familie: to ordein ſtrength out of the mouthes of Babes &amp; ſucklinges aginſt the enemy; that vvold deny our Lords ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelogie. The Ievves all, but the hand laborers, brought vp their<note place="margin">Maim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny in Thalmud Thorah.</note> children from ſeauen to fourtene, in lerning the plain tongue; &amp; all their time, for ſome fevv hovvres vvekely; not minding gaines therby; but the delite to knovv God. And ſuch haue bene to heathen the Salvation of our ſtate. And aſſemblies of ſuch ſagely opening ſcripture vvold much edifie. And vvher the King is lerned, fevv yeres vvold frame vniverſities to that courſe; to make thouſandes of ſound ſkill in the Bibles tongues &amp; matter. So vve ſhould mark vveighty matters cloſly contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in fevv vvordes; &amp; Sophonyes caſtinge off Salomons
<pb facs="tcp:152051:13"/> ſaing: This ſhall come to paſſe: In that day I vvill make a rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Princes; &amp; of the Kinges Sonnes. In the dayes of Ioſias Sophonie ſpake this ch. 1. 8. Now the Sonnes of Ioſias were Iohn, the firſt begoten in Kinges phraſe: othervviſe yonger then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oakim tvvo yeres; but reigning firſt, he is firſt ſonne of the Kindome. Next is Ioakim properly the Eldeſt: next Sedekias, who reigning after his brothers ſonne, is called in Kinges phraſe, Iechonias ſon. Novv of theſe Iohn or Ioa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas was ſone caryed to Egypt, &amp; died in priſon: vnlamented Ier 22. Ioakim vvas caried for Babel. 2. k. 25. &amp; died by the vvay: &amp; vvas caſt avvay vnburied; to the buriall of an aſſe, as he brent Ieremies Lamentationes. Sedekias had in the ende his eyes pulled out; for rebellion againſt the King of Babel; &amp; his children vvere Killed before his face: 2. k. 25. vvhen the high ſacrificer Saraias father to Ezra vvas killed. That ſtory of Sarai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as death-time vvill ſerve anone to great vſe, for Dan. 9.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Of Iechonias God ſvvare that he should die, leaving no child alive behind him; vvherefore, it vvere flat Atheiſme, to prate that he naturally became Father to Salathiel. Though S. Luke had never left vs Salathiels family Vp to Natha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvhole brother to Salomon; to shevv that Salatiel vvas of another fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie; Gods oth should make vs beleeue that, vvithout any fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther recorde, Ier. 22. So God made a riddance of the Ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean race of Iorams. And vve are cloſly vvarned of that in the names <hi>Ner-i</hi> &amp; <hi>Melch-i,</hi> comparing them vvith Sophonies Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phecy, and the Kings ſtory; shevving the truth of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, That Nathan his houſe loked for the Eternal kingdomes prerogative. They vvho vvill nor build ſuch Gold from the moſt kingly familie, had great neede of Colyrion to annointe their eies.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Of Salathiel vve muſt conſider manie poincts, beginning in, Name. Samuel &amp; Salathiel are both one; Anna the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther called his name Samuel, becauſe of God Saalti, I have prayed to haue him. Novv Samuel vvas borne at the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:152051:13"/> of the glory from Sylo &amp; Ephraim of Ioſephs houſe vnto Iuda our Lord his Tribe. So vvas Salathiel borne at the fall &amp; end of Salomons race; &amp; at the remouing of the glory vnto Nathan, that Nathan the Prophet might be called into mind for old Samuel, vvho taught of Chriſt his true kingdome.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Compare the contrarie Prophecies of Iechonias &amp; Sal.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Prophecie of Iechonias.</head>
               <p>As I live<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaith the Eternal, yf Chonias the ſon of Ioakim King of Iudah, vvere a ſignet upon my right hand, I vvold pluck thee thence. O earth. earth, earth, heare the vvord of the Lord: vvrite ye this man Conias childles, a man that shal not proſper in all his dayes, for none shall grovv from his ſede, to ſit vpon the throne of David; or to beare rule anie more in Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>da. Thus all may ſee a plain end of Salomons houſe; and hovv dangerouſly thoſe Doctors be deceaved, vvho bring Chriſt from Iechonias. They are litle better vvho take in hand to teach, and make not this plain to the ſimpleſt. The Bishop of our ſoules vvil hate ſuch blind contemners.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Zorobabel, Agg. 2.</head>
               <p>Thus Aggai ſealeth his Prophecy; In that day, ſaith the Eternal of hoſtes, I vvill take thee Zorobabel ſon of Salathiel, &amp; I vvill make thee as a ſigne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; for thee have I choſen, ſaith the<note place="margin">An he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auenly tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the title Pſ. 22.</note> Eternal of hoſtes. This concluſion of Aggai, compared vvith Gods oth againſt Iechonias, should have ſtayed vs from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiring vvith the dogges that deſpiſed <hi>Aieleth ha Sachar</hi> Pſ. 22 The morning ſtar, as our Lord Ap. 3. and 22. &amp; kimchi there, tranſlate the Ebr. He hath not yet davvned to ſuch Doctors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of zacharie teaching hovv zorobabel cometh of Nathan, chap. 10. 12.</head>
               <p>Thus zacharie joineth to Aggei; In that day the Land shall lament ech familie apart; the familie of David apart, &amp; their vviues apart; the familie of the houſe of Nathan apart, &amp; their vviues apart; the familie of the houſe of Levi apart, and their vvives apart; the familie of Semei apart, &amp; their vvives apart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:14"/>
               <head>The notation of Zorobabel.</head>
               <p>Zorobabel his name conteineth the ſtately prophecy of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels fall; vvher vvith Ieremy comforteth Iuda. ch. 51. 2. I will ſend againſt Babel, Zor-im; fanners, vvhich Zor o Babel. Mark here vvith-all hovv the golden head is fanned to chaff. And this much doth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Zorobabel conteine in name. And vvhen Babel the houſe of Nemrod &amp; Cham vver fanned by Sem &amp; Iapheth, then cometh an Angel to tell vvhen Chriſt the ſignet of God from Zorobabel ſhould be ſealed: that all men might reckon from yere to yere, hovv nere they came to the Kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>of ther names notation.</head>
               <p>As Zorobabel vvas alſo called Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>betzar, glad in affliction; ſo his eldeſt ſon vvas called Moſollam: that is: he ſhalbe ſettled in Salem; as Naaſſon called Salmon in that ſenſe, ſo he is called 1. chr. 3. &amp; by an other notation, Abihu; Math. 1. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſonne is called Ananias; in remembrance of Ananias the noble martyr, the glory of men; that quenched the fyer. He vvas fitly termed ſo; a father to Chriſt; that quencheth Hell fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from burning his ſervantes; The ſame man is called by an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name Rheſa, principal; being the ſecond brother; Becauſe he that is principall over all, ſhall come from him; &amp; make the ſecond brother principal to the firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Names from famous ancient men.</head>
               <p>The name of Nathan Dauids ſonne might not be geuen to moo; as no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e but one vvas called Dauid, nor any in the right Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to Adam: to kepe the ſtory from confuſion. But the Like in notation are full many. Nathan is, HE (God) geveth &amp; Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatha, Matthat, Mattathias tvviſe coming, &amp; Matth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> n Mat. 1. be all reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brances of Nathan Dauids ſonne; named after the prophet, vvhich promiſed Chriſt to Dauid. So they ſtill knevv that Chriſt ſhould come of them. So Ianna, ſhort, or Ioanna longe, Iona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the lxx expreſſe Ebrevv, all be Iohn: by vvhich name Iohaiada the good high ſacrificer vvas called. So the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb facs="tcp:152051:14"/> Melchi, Amos &amp; Nachum reuiue ſtories, &amp; loke for Kingdome, ſtrenght &amp; comfort; So Elmodam reuiueth the ſtory of Iockta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Elmodad vvher to avoyd loth ſome doublyng of D. the one is changed. Iocktans houſe highly angred God; falling to Babels Idols after many from, Sem Arphaxad, Sela, &amp; Eber, folovved the godly fathers. Therfore God ſcattered them further to fill eaſt &amp; vveſt India. Yet Chriſt vvold once call all; &amp; one of his fathers ſhevved that, in his name, from Iocktanes Eldeſt ſon Elmodad. Others haue religions foundation, as loſe, all one to Ieſus, a Saviour; Eliezer, God hath ſtrengh, Iorim, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liakim God ſetteth vp. Her, the vigilant. Theſe conteine the ground of religion; Others touched the lot of the particular familie; As Malea fulnes, Majnan, vvaters of encreaſe; vvhen Roboams houſe vvas decaying quickly. Some expreſs the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers confort in a ſonne, as Cheſly, my glory, Addy an orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> &amp; one remembrance of hard lot; Mahath, vexation. All be vvittely named; &amp; our Lord Er the Aey vigilant, ſayth; ye ſhall not ſeke me in vain. An idle ſyllable ſhall not be found in the names of Ieſus his fathers. By theſe argumentes the vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Ievves that reiect the Kinges record knovven over natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes might be avvnſvveared &amp; muſſelled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Cainan, ioyned to Arphaxad; vvhich Cainan neuer vvas in the vvorld.</head>
               <p>S. Luke ſhevveth to all lerned in tongues that he folovved the very ſyllables of publiq recordes: othervviſe moo names from one Hebrevv as Ianna, Ioanna, &amp; Ionan, he had expreſſed in one tenour. So he folovveth the lxx for Cainan, ſon, as it was ſuppoſed, to Aaphaxad. the lxx knevv that he never vvas in the vvorld; as nether Cainan the ſixt ſon to Sem; Gen. 10. in the lxx; as they knevv that; Ioſeph vvas father but to Manaſſes &amp; Ephraim: vvhen Iacob came to Egypt; &amp; not yet to the fiue added by them gen. 46 ch. vvhich make for Ebrevv lxx ſoules; in the lxx. they make 75. vvhich thing alſo S. Luke folovveth act. 7. I haue in my Conſent ſhevved the reaſon. But here alſo
<pb facs="tcp:152051:15"/> it may fiitly be handled: yet a long diſcourſe muſt come to open the vvhole nature of the matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why the lxx hid their mind.</head>
               <p>The lxx ij Ievves, ſix for every tribe are named, in ſhortnes lxx. vvhen Ptolemy Philadelphus ambitious of a great librarie ſent to Iudah, to haue them bookes in Greke; ſo many tranſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vvere ſent to Egypt vvith the holy volume; vvhich they tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Greke; but vvith exceding departing from the Ebrevv. And they caryed not vvith them the pomcted Bible, that they might more frely dally vvith the prophane heathen. One ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample may be in the yeres a thouſand &amp; many hundre the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vvhich they feigned. Of that I haue vvritten at large to Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedeck. An other ſtrange departing from Ebrevv appeareth in Gen. 4 to this Ebrevv vnpoincted:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Halo im tetib sheeth, ve im lo tetib le petach chatathrobets.</hi> or thus <hi>le patteach, chatatha; Rebatz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is ther not vpon vvell doing, recompence? and yf thou do not vvells ſyns pay is nere at the dore. Becauſe heathen ſhould not plead henſe in heathen maner; Do vvell, &amp; haue vvell, they adde vovvls thus; yf thou offre well, &amp; devide not vvell, thou haſt ſinned; be quiet. And this mockage they thought fitteſt for heathen ſcorners of truth. This vvas the vvell doing, ſpoken by God; That Cain, yf he vvold come to God, muſt beleue that God is; &amp; is a revvarder of them that ſeke him. But Lagidae &amp; Chemmis land, vvold not ſone conceaue this ſenſe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that ſitteth in heauen vvold ſcorne them: &amp; the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall vvold make a mock of them. For this rule was from the beginnig; Caſt not pearles to hogges; nor holy thinges to dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
               <p>An other daliance vvas this: Deut. 32. when the only High ſcattered the ſonnes of Adam, he ſettled the borders of natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes according to the number of the Angels of God. The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew hath: According to the number of the ſonnes of Iſrael. They ſavv vveighty cauſe of this dalliance; vvhich I haue prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a dedication to my Grek tranſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the prophets dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
<pb facs="tcp:152051:15"/> to the B. of Mentz.</p>
               <p>The 2. Pſalme ſpeaketh in this ſort. Kiſſe the ſonne leſt he be angry; vvher is anger ſone Kindled. Happy are all that truſt in him. Fleſh &amp; blood could not open this vnto the vvorld, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the father which is in heauen ſhould reveale it. How God ſo loued the world that he gaue his only begoten ſon, to the end that vvhſoeuer beleue on him ſhould not periſh but haue lift everlaſtinge. At this they would haue skoffed; as hovv often ſkoffed they the King of glory in the dayes of his fleſh. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the holy vvordes vvhich proprely ſay Kiſſe the Son, they turne craftily thus; Lay hould vpod doſtrine leſt. vvicked men ſhould ſay: Dauid maketh him ſelf the Son of God.</p>
               <p>So they vvere in danger of more then ſkoffing, in a comon brag. Thus they triumphed: as yet recordes ſhevv in Zohar v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon exod; <hi>Col. 27. IACOB OVR father went to Egypt with LXX Soules: to recover the LXX families which curſed Cham bred by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted tongues for Babels Idolous tower. And the ſeauenty ſoules of Iacob match in valew all the families of the world; &amp; he that will rule over them is as great a tyrant as an vſurper to reine ouer all the world.</hi> This bragge all Barbers &amp; blear-eyed knevv; &amp; yf they had not hid the trueth of lxx families Gen. 10. &amp; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvhat in Gen. xj. by tvvo feined Cainans, &amp; by fiue Gen. 46. fiue then not borne, they had bene more in danger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder Aman; differing from all nationes in the feaſt of tabernacles; For that vvas their greateſt open difference, as the Chaldy Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther toucheth. The lxx having thus dealed, &amp; the Sanedrin or Synedrion having enacted a lavv that none ſhould alter the lxx. Euſeb praep. 8. S. Luke vvas to folovv the Greke; as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder; &amp; not as a judge both in Cainan; &amp; in ſoules 75. act. 7. And he vvrote not to Siculis &amp; Conſentinis; but to vviſe men that had their eies in theri head. He vvho vpon act. 7. feigneth that ſome late man added fiue act. 7. &amp; to the lxxij gen. 46. vvold make all the Chriſtianes in the vvorld very ſimple; that could not eſpie that; but marre all copies; &amp; Arabiq tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones.
<pb facs="tcp:152051:16"/> Moreover vvhat vvill he ſay to the old Greke Philo; Equallaged to S. Luke; handling Abrahams 75. yeres &amp; Iacob 75. ſoules Gen. 46. &amp; exod. 1. &amp; again but 70 in Deut. 10. 22. He diſcanting after his maner telleth hovv in dalliance ſoules vvere 75. in trueth but lxx. That number of fiue then vnbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to Ioſeph, I vvil not here declare vvhy to him more then to other enlargement vvas; &amp; vvhy the number of fiue: my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent &amp; aduertiſement conferred may giue aduertiſement. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Cainan one ſayth he had a copy vvhich had not Cay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan. I can vvell beleue it. For vvher the Apoſtles excede in vviſdome: as S. Mathevv in omitting hatefull Ioakim, ſome vvicked praeſumptuous copier vvold nedes amend the text; to ſay for; Ioſias begate Iechonias &amp; his brethren; that is, Sede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kias the vncle that reigned after him: Ioſias begate Iakim: Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kim begate Iechonias &amp; his brethren. Geneva printed this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 60 yeres; &amp; vvith their folollovvers filled Europe vvith corrupt copies. Yet Beza revoked the vvicked copie; But vvho can revoke the milliones of the corrupted. The old conſent of the Church hauing truth, ſhould haue ſtood as vvell at the firſt as at the laſt: &amp; a tovvne that feared God, ſhould not brag hovv they giue the beſt Bible vvher they miſſe moſt deadly. And ſo vvhen they leaue out Cainan here Luc. 3. vvhen God ſet him in the text: pretending a vvarrant as praeſumptuous that they ſavv a copy void of that Cainan<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they ſhould not be folovved in England. Morouver marke this; that Grekes in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius make Abraham the tenth after Noe in ſtory: though the 70 vvold make him the eleventh: &amp; ſo Epiphanius maketh Iacob not the tvventy three, but after the Ebrevv the tvventy tvvo. And I had an Arabiq commen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arie vpon Geneſis vvhich in dede folovved the lxx but vvith a note of miſli king: But novv I haue not that. For one Mattathias Holmes caried my Arabiq bookes &amp; Bibles Maſſorite, &amp; greate Plantine &amp; others the beſt in the vvorld all mine, to Ierne-land; &amp; at his death told as M. Trauerſe vvill teſtifie &amp; others that they vvere
<pb facs="tcp:152051:16"/> mine, yet one that maryed his ſiſter, dealt vvorſe then any Turk; he ſould them as his bookes of 100 lib ſterling, lent of curteſie; vvithout any peny l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt for pavvne: as, Middleburge knovveth. I humbly requeſt the King to call him to accompts &amp; all others to hould him as he deſerueth for euer. Yf my ovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne book had bene left me, Canian from Arabia might be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled. And this much for S. Luke. Only one bad note of a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevean calling the Goſpell into doubt, I muſt touch. He vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth hovv he hath a copy venerandae vetuſtatis, vvher not S. Lukes men, but S. Mathevves be vp vnto Adam. He ſhould haue brent, not ſent to poſterity that vvicked vvork. Some vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked copier, that dreamed Ioſeph his familie, to be handled in S. Luke, and knovving that Ioſeph could not haue naturall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in ſeverall families, thought good to frame a Goſpell of his ovvne head: &amp; to leaue out the moſt glorious familie in the vvorld. This rule the reader may take at my hand: <hi>That comonly the places in which the holy Apoſtles excell in Thalmudi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> or Atti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Lerning, ſome rude copiers alter after their owne braine.</hi> But as any eares can diſcerne Cyclops Polyphemus Muſike to come ſhort of Ariſtoxenus: ſo any one Thalmudi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; Atti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vvhat the holy Apoſtles left, Rude copiers can never bring that vvhich hath rare vviſdome. So the copie of rare vviſdome muſt nedes be holden the copy of God: vvhen ther is difference betvvixt the barbarous &amp; them. And the church in moſt Greke copies &amp; old Arabiq, folovv the beſt. And none but voyd of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; vvicked vvranglers, vvill deny that both teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſtand in the original ſure enough for copy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>What vſe the forged Canian hath.</head>
               <p>The fooliſh of God is vviſer then Men. The lxx departing from Ebrevv truth, becauſe heathen vvold not ſuffer it, ſhevv for all Diuinity, hovv the natural man cannot abide it. Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally they ſhevved, that in the 75 ſoules &amp; in Cainan. And that vvold our Lord teach Children in his ovvne familie; Bringing irony or mockage for a Cainan that never vvas in the vvorld.
<pb facs="tcp:152051:17"/> And by a man, that never vvas a man, teache wicked men, how they will become worſe then nothinge: eternally miſerable. So the forged Cainan hath great vſe; &amp; corrupt tranſlations after corrupt copies ſhould not be ſold vnamended, after vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge: ſuch as leaue out Cainan vvhom God left vs. And ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially becauſe Ievves in every corner be thornes in our ſides, &amp; prickes in our eyes, vve ſhould loth help to them; as in vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked blaming the moſt heauenly purenes of the Greke teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And this much for our Lordes fathers ſet in S. Luke vnto Dauid. The notationes of all from Adam to Dauid conteyne the Abridgement of their ſtory. But the vnebrevved vvold not ſone conceaue them. All vviſe ſtudentes that take to Diuinity vvill lerne the holy tongue: &amp; ſuch, of them ſelues may ſone ſee vvhat the names import. Novv Let vs look hovv S. Mathevv ſhevveth Meſſias to be man, Emmanuel, (as S. Luke) from Abraham to Dauid: &amp; to be God in man: &amp; King of the Ievves. Theſe be the groundes of our faith: &amp; our darkenes vvilbe exceding great, yf vve miſſe in theſe poinctes. S. Mathevves text ſhalbe firſt layd dovvne, vvith ſo much of the perſones ſtory as principally argueth doctrine for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the vvorld to come: &amp; of right faith in them, as in vs novv. The fathers of our Lord the firſt fourtene ſhould haue their ſtory knovven among their ſpirituall ſonnes, to beimita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of vs; &amp; the Kinges ſhould be knovven: to conſider im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectiones, arguing that Chriſt his Kingdome ſhould not be as an earthly one. Novv the third rovv, vvill force vs to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine ſtately ſtories of their enemies deſtruction: &amp; hovv they by Daniel ſeauens, did knovv vvhen. Chriſt vvold come into the vvorld; &amp; there I muſt defend our church: &amp; many others againſt betrayers of the truth vnto Ievves: vpon that occaſion in ſundry ſortes. They notoriouſhy vexe vs for our Doctours Babyſhnes for confunding our Lordes holy fathers, vvith Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bean Kinges of Roboams Ammonean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace; &amp; for diſagreing for redemption time; &amp; for Daniels fourth Kingdome.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:152051:17"/>
            <head>OF THE FATHERS CITED IN S. Mathevv his holy text.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
               <hi>book of the Kindred of IESVS Christ: the ſonne of Dauid: the ſonne of Abraham. Abraham begate Iſaac. Iſaac begate Iacob. Iacob begate Iudas, &amp; his brethren. Iudas begate Phares, &amp; Zara, of Thamar. Phares begate Eſrom. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom begate Aram. Aram begate Aminadab. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minadab begate Naaſſon. Naaſson begate Salmon. Salmon begate Booz of Rachab. Booz begate Obed of Ruth. Obed begate Ieſſaj. Ieſſaj begate Dauid the Kinge. Dauid the King begate Salomon, of her vvhich vvs Vriaes. Salomon begate Roboam. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam begate Abia. Abia begate Aſa. Aſa begate Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat. Ioſaphat begate Ioram. Ioram begate Ozi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Ozias begate Ioatham. Ioatham begate Achaz. Achaz begate Ezechias. Ezechias begate Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſſes. Manaſſes begate Amon. Amon begate Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias.
<pb facs="tcp:152051:18"/> Ioſias begate Iechonias, &amp; his brethren nere the captiuity of Babylon. After the captiuitie of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon Iechonias begate Salathiel. Salathiel begate</hi>
               <note place="margin">as a King for a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour: as Baaſa for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab. 1. King 20.</note> 
               <hi>Zorobabel. Zorobabel begate Abihud. Abihud be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Eliakim. Eliakim begate Azor. Azor begate Sadok. Sadok begate Achim. Achim begate Elihud. Elihud begate Eleazar. Eleazar begate Matthan. Matthan begate Iacob. Iacob begate Ioſeph the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of Mary, of vvhich vvas begotten IESVS, vvhich is called Christ. So all the generations from Abraham to Dauid, are fourteene generations: And from Dauid vntill the captiuity of Babylon, fourteene generations: and after the captiuity of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon vntill Chriſt, fourteenegenerations. Novv the berth of Ieſus Chriſt vvas thus. When his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Marj vvas betrothed to Ioſeph, before they came together, she vvas found vvith child of the holy Ghoſt. Novv Ioſeph her husband being agra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious man: &amp; vnvvilling to make her cauſe ſeen, vvold haue put her avvay ſecretly. And as he vvas thus minded, Behold, the angel of the Lord appeared to him in a dreame ſayng: Ioſeph ſonne of Dauid feare not to take Mary, thy vvife. For that vvhich is begoten in her is of the holy Ghoſt. For, she shall
<pb facs="tcp:152051:18"/> bear a ſonne: &amp; thou shalt call his name Ieſus: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he shall ſaue his people from their ſinnes. And all this came to paſſe to fullfill that vvhich vvas ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Lord by Eſaj the prophet, ſayng. Behould a virgin shalbe vvith child, &amp; shall beare a ſonne, &amp; his name shalbe called, Emmanuel, vvhich is by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, God vvith vs. Then Ioſeph avva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out of ſlepe: &amp; did as the Angel of the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded him, &amp; toke his vvife: but knevv her not, vntill she bare her ſonne, the first-borne &amp; called his name, IESVS.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Obſervationes.</head>
               <p>This narration dependeth vpon the demaund of the Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Philoſophers, vvho by Daniels prophecy, ch. 9. came to Ieruſalem, to ſeke the late borne King of the Ievves the moſt holy. Daniel the vviſe, full of grace, vvold not miſſe to take or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that his nation &amp; Suſan vvher is rombe vvas yet honored of Elam, ſhould reckon moſt exactly yere by yere, vvhen the King of glory vvold make his covenant, vvith all nationes. And the half ſeauen, of teaching the Goſpell, vvas made knovven; &amp; thirty yeres for to be a father in nature, Solon the old &amp; Heſiod noted in poetry; &amp; Sala, Paleg, Saruch, our Lords fathers ſhevv it in practiſe, fathers at thirty. And for governement; Ioſeph as King in Egypt at thirty; &amp; Dauid King in dede at Hebron: &amp; the lavv for the Levites to begin their office of ſad or heay charge at thirty. So all the vvorld as the Philoſophers of Suſan might knovv in vvhat yere ſince Iudah came from Babel, Chriſt vvas to come into the vvorld.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:19"/>
               <p>And a comfortable light in the ayer appearing at Suſan ſtrange aboue the courſe of nature, could not but move the Perſian lerned men, to knovv Gods counſel, to loke for the King, told off by holy Daniel, ſo longe before. For this cauſe the Perſians Sages come to Ieruſalem. But Herod better knevv the time, as the Sacrificers &amp; the vvhole nation; of vvhom none brought exception that vvay; none of any ſtriving againſt the truth, for other poinctes. But Herod miſtoke the nature of the King; &amp; knevv not that God vvas in Chriſt, reconciling the vvorld vnto him ſelf. To teach Herod, &amp; the Thalmudi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; all the vvorld, vvhat kind of King Meſſias ſhould be, S. Mathevv vvriteth this chapter; ſhevving fourtene, fathers after the fleſh to the ſonne Eternal; vvho ſavv his dayes afore &amp; rejoyced; &amp; although they vvere nor perfitect in doctrine ſeuerally from vs; yet heauen, the perfect bleſſing for the ſoule, they had vvhen they left this vvorld. All good men in priuate life; But the firſt King hardly ſaued him ſelf; after he came to reſt. Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene be of them: After them come fourtene Kinges: fathers for the Kingdome: but not natural fathers, to Chriſt all faulty, for governement, &amp; many, greatly ſinful; &amp; not in Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. So, S. Mathew doth teach ſuch as knew the law, that Chriſt his Kingdome was not of this world. And he leaueth Salomons houſe: vvhoſe natural ſucceſſion did end vvith Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chonias: &amp; thence he cometh to Salathiel, of Nathan: &amp; to zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rob. vvho ar <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And then he turneth aſide to the Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges line: vvher be ten. Mary &amp; Ieſus make vp the third fovver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene: and all be called in Daniel heyres of the Eternal King<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome. Great matters depend vpon their ſtory: vvherby all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhould be conſidered ſeverally; as they are ſeverally ſet dovvne for that purpoſe. And the principal matters that touched their ſtory, ſhall be handled vvith them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the firſt fovvertene; &amp; of Abraham ſeverally.</head>
               <p>Dauid the King is once named firſt, becauſe Herod demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the King; &amp; to Dauid firſt, the Eternal Kingdome vvas
<pb facs="tcp:152051:19"/> promiſed. After a touch that vvay, Abraham is ſet fyrſt &amp; the reſt in order to make fourtene; vvher the laſt is King.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Why Abraham geueth the beginning of the ſtory.</head>
               <p>The Land of Chanaan vvher the Kingdome ſhould ariſe, vvas firſt promiſed to Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; Chriſt vvas promiſed to him firſt of any man in open diſtinct plain vvordes. And he is made father of the heathen; vvhich vvold folovv his beliefe; &amp; the heathen might offer firſt frutes at Ieruſalem; as Maimony no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Bechor. Per. 4. So for Ievves &amp; gentiles the beginning from him is very fit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Abrahams glory.</head>
               <p>Abraham is often commended vnto vs; vvhoſe commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation all his children by faith ſhould gladly knovv &amp; publiſh. He left the field of the Chaldeans being nere Babel, in the moſt propre Meſopotamia nere the meting of the tvvo rivers Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris &amp; Euphrates; &amp; ſtayd at Charan till he make many Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les; &amp; his father died there, aged 205. yeres. heauy by yeres, who toke his journey for Chanaan, &amp; had not broken off, but by heauy yeres, &amp; death: then was Abraham 75. by Moyſes text: by S. ſtephans note vpon it; by the Greke Philo; whoſe (wordes I haue cited in the Concent in Latin:) &amp; by ſundry Ebrewes in Midras Rabba. And reaſon wold tell vs that Thara was dead before God promiſed Abraham that Chriſt ſhould come of him: Otherwiſe as he took journey tovvard Chanaan; he had not ſtayd in Charan but by vveakenes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>An aunſvvear to M. Scaliger.</head>
               <p>Becauſe it is vvritten Thara liued ſeauenty yeres, &amp; begate Abraham, Charan &amp; Nachor, M. ſcaliger fighteth vehemently againſt Beroaldus &amp; all that vvere afore of his mynd. And vvher he ſaith, ſtill brethren be named in ſeniority; &amp; for the obiection in Sem, Cham, &amp; Iapheth; vvher Iapheth is eldeſt in the lxx he vvold haue Sem eldeſt, Cham next &amp; Iapheth yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, I aunſvvear; yf any vvil be contentions the church of God hath no ſuch cuſtome to S. ſtephen act. 7. he ſayd: None yet
<pb facs="tcp:152051:20"/> vnderſtood S. Luke. Then vvher is the fault in our vvit, or i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his pen? And in Bathſhebaes ſonnes 1. Chr. 3. Salomon the Eldeſt is named laſt; &amp; Nathan the ſecond is named third. And Ioachaz the ſecond ſonne of Ioſias both is named firſt, &amp; called the firſt borne. And ſeing Iſcha or Sara vvas Harans daughter &amp; but ten yeres yonger then Abraham, the Babylonian Thal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mud gathereth ſenſibly that Abraham vvas not the Eldeſt. So all the Eldeſt Ievves fight for S. ſtephen; &amp; for S. Luke. And for S. Mathevv that Thara vvas dead before Abraham recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the promiſſe. That ſtill Abraham might be alone in the dignity of the promeſſe. So M. ſcaliger might haue ſpared di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance of S. Mathevves begininge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Abrahams Idolatry.</head>
               <p>S. Paul calleth Abraham <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as he vvas once Idolatrous; &amp; ſuch an one Philo &amp; Rambam make him to haue bene; but by faith he vvas iuſtified. So S. Paul diſputeth vpon him; againſt the Ievves thus; vvhat ſhall vve ſay then that Abraham our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther found by the fleſh? yf Abraham vvere iuſtefied by vvorkes he hath vvherin to reioyce. But he hath no vvorkes to reioice in before God For his requeſt vnto Sara to hazard her Chaſtity vvas a fault; as Rabby Bechaia vpon gen. 15 doth make it, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregious treſpas, a groſs fault, an exceding ſin; bred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruſt in God; &amp; the cauſe of Iſraels ſorovv &amp; fall in Egypt. So he hath not to rejoice before God: Therfore he vvas not iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by vvorkes before God. S. Iames dealing vvith Ievves vvho then, as novv, think theyr reverence to the lavv, &amp; belief in the trueth of the ſtory, iuſtifyes them, ſhevveth that they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued. For Abraham &amp; all Godly ſhevv good vvorkes, to tell others that they honour God; as Abraham did: in not ſparing his Sonne. Novv, vvher as God ſayd to Abraham; Becauſe thou haſt not ſpared thy only ſonne; I ſvveare, I vvill multiply thy ſede; The very Ievves in Midras Rabba ſhevv the meaning thus; by the ſimilitude of a phyſician, vvho promiſeth to heale a great man of a dangerous ſicknes; &amp; after his promeſs geueth
<pb facs="tcp:152051:20"/> a moſt bitter potion; vvhich the patient taketh boldly; &amp; then the phyſician ſayth; Becauſe you haue ſo taken the drench; I vvill ſvvear I vvill heale you. Thus the party is confirmed; &amp; not called to a nevv beginnig. So Abrahams manifeſtation of regeneration is re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ompenſed, in a confirmation: not vvith the fountain of his iuſtification. And ſtill the Prophetes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire open iuſtice; &amp; God puniſheth every ſin; but leſſe, vpon charity; &amp; in that ſenſe charity covereth many ſinnes. But the fountaine vvas Abraham beleued in God: &amp; that vvas recok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to him for iuſtice; as Dauid ſayth that they are happy vvhoſe ſinnes are forgiuen. So Abraham vvas iuſtified by faith; beleving that Chriſt ſbould come of him; &amp; ſhould be raiſed from the dead, as he knevv that yf he had killed Iſaac God wold haue raiſed him again. So faith ſhalbe reckoned vnto vs for iuſtice; vvich beleue that God raiſed Ieſus our Lord from the dead: vvho vvas killed for our ſinnes: &amp; raiſed for our iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Theſe poinctes the Greke Crede handleth plainly; &amp; the Greke fathers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; Porphyry and the oracles, that our Lordes ſoule vvent hence to heauen. And Ben Arama, vvho ſaith; Chriſtianes beleue our Lordes ſoule vvent to Hell, doth the Goſpell great iniury. Fot through infinite mention of death &amp; reſurrection, ther is never one ſyllable of going to Hell but in one oration in Iohn ſix times expreſſ mentio of going to the father. A vviſe vvriter never repeates, but vvith ſome addition yf any can be. And ſeing the going of a iuſt ſoule to Hell, is more ſtrange, then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the dvvelling of God in man; or reſurrection; it had bene oftener handled in plain termes, yf it had bene true. One R. Man a Ievv obiected vnto me our Crede of going to Hell. I told him it vvas an heathen phraſe; but meaned, as theyr Thalmudi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> to go to Parad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe; &amp; So deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending in Moſes Ioſue, Iudges, Ruth, &amp; Kinges, is for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; ſo tranſlated; &amp; more then once tranſlated <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. And <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to go is tranſlated Aſcend &amp; Deſcend &amp; So <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is vſed of paſſage; as from Nazareth to Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naum
<pb facs="tcp:152051:21"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aum in our Lord: &amp; exceding often in the actes of the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: and Hades, for Abraham, is heauen or Paradiſe. For as Britanie conteyneth tvvo partes, England &amp; Scotland; So Hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des conteyneth Heauen &amp; Hell; &amp; in Abraham ſet in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nig of the Nevv Teſtament, God vvold vſe Haides Luc. 16 &amp; tell expreſly that God praepared Heauen to receaue Abraham the pilgrom &amp; ſtranger, loking for the heauenly city. &amp; hence the Ievves might haue lerned the meaning of our Crede: &amp; for Paradiſe Luc. 23. the matter vvas plain; that our L. vvent thence thither. And no Ievves of Modeſty vvold haue ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered our Goſpell to Mach mad: to forge beter Keys of Paradiſe. A pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſtical Black ſmith, not a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſaleel he proued. Although this article ſhould here be handled largely in Abraham the Patron of faith; yet I may be ſhort: becauſe L. Th. vvinton proveth againſt Geueveans by Ioſephus, Ignatius, Iuſtin mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, Euſebius, Athanaſius, (in his ſermon) Cyrillus, Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Nazianzen, That Haides or Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>achthonia to Godly, is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; &amp; he fortifieth Geneveans faith; that by Grek our Lord vvent hence to Paradiſe; &amp; iuſtly reiecteth Hell grefe from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as hated of Bible, Rabbines vpon Ebrevv, &amp; Attiques vpon the Goſpell. I ſhevved in ſix Greke vvorkes left in Germanie hovv lernedly the R. R. F. healed the Geneveans diſeaſe; vvho denyed a going to Haides vvher Abraham is; Luc. 16. &amp; all faithfull ſoules, to croſſe theyr ovvne faith: &amp; deny ſoules im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality: &amp; vvold haue all heathean, enemies for f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endes; &amp; all Greke fathers, enemies, for frendes offering help. In that lerned paines, fortifying Geneva, L. W. doeth confute DD. B. &amp; B. Purgatorie &amp; Limbum. And vvith Abrahams ſtory Children learne Abrahams religion; for the trinity, Incarnation, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; &amp; Paradiſe hence receauing the faithfull, as hoat fyer, the vvicked; &amp; not to be vvaving vvith every vvind of Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Diuinity. The notation of Abraham is an high father of many nationes handled Rom. 4. from Geneſis Ch. 17.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:21"/>
               <head>Of Iſaac.</head>
               <p>Abraham after the fleſh begate Iſmael: vvhence came the vncleane ſpirit of Machmad, &amp; that nation the poyſon of the vvorld. Yet Iſaac, though conceaued in ſin, as others, vvas quickened vvith Chriſt: and raiſed, &amp; placed in heauen vvith him; vvho being vvilling to die, knevv that he ſhould be raiſed vp again; Faith vvas in him the ſtay of thinges hoped for; &amp; tryer out of thinges not ſene. In Iſaac ſhall Abrahams ſede be called. But Eſavv of Iſaac caſt off God; a profane man: vvho ſold his birthright for a meſs of Pottage. Iſaaks name is laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; or gladnes; the Ioy of the vvorld. Iacob in name is a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planter; as Eſavv complaineth, he tvviſe ſupplanted him Gen. 28. He ſhevved moſt plainly his hope for riches, in Chriſt his Kingdom; vvhen he requeſted no more but diet &amp; clothing gen. 28. Iob &amp; Paul teach all to folovv him Iob. 3. 1. Tim. 6. Yea and this Epigramme diuine from one prophane.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>Naked came I vnto the vvorld, &amp; naked go I into the earth; &amp; vvhat labour I in vaine; ſeing a naked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Iacob ſavv a lather, reaching from the earth to heauen; &amp; God vvas in the top of it; &amp; Angels aſcended &amp; deſcended by it. He knevv that Chriſt vvas the Sonne of God; &amp; that Angels ſhould aſcend &amp; deſcend vpon the ſonne of man; yf Herod had knovven ſo much, he had not ſought to kill the lateborne King of the Ievves. The Trinity Iacob knevv; &amp; nameth one &amp; the ſame Angel that vvreſtled vvith him, the Angel that vvold bleſs Ioſeph; &amp; the God of Bethel. And he taught his tvvelue Sonnes not to ſay: vvho can go vp to heauen to bring Chriſt dovvne? or vvho can go dovvne into the depe of the earth, to bring Chriſt from the dead; but to beleue that the God of Bethel vvold come man of him, &amp; of Iuda: &amp; that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as S. Paul Rom. 4. tranſlateth Eſ. 53 after the 70 vvold
<pb facs="tcp:152051:22"/> pour his ſoule to death; &amp; be recovered from death; as Iſaac in type; &amp; go from the croſs to the father; &amp; that all the faithfull ſhould ſo do; as the nevv Teſtament teacheth continually; That Iſaac Ben Arama after old Siphri might be aſhamed to ſay our Goſpel beleued that ether the Prophets or old iuſt, or our Lord euer vvent to Hell. The Church never beleued that; But the Deuels here triumph over ſuch teachers. God left his vvord ſure: &amp; teacheth nothing in corners. And they are gods hated for Lerning that dreame of proving rules of faith from corners. The Patriarches reſted in the incarnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And our Crede Goeth no further for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is any paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, vp, dovvn; Ether term is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon for journeys in al autours &amp; all Kind of vvriters ſpeak ſo; &amp; Haides moſt be told inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly to Babes that it is heauen in the light part for the Godly; as in the dark part hell for the vvicked. The dull &amp; vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vvightes that raue againſt this, ſhall ſee Iſaak &amp; Iacob in Abrahams boſom in Haides; but in their courſe they haſt vp to Gehennia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Iudah &amp; his brethren.</head>
               <p>The tvvelue Patriarkes might haue taught Herod of what nature the Kingdome of Chriſt vvas. Ruben ſavv nothing here but Sorovv. Yet he liueth Eternally &amp; paſſed from death to life; Symeon &amp; Levy heard of a curſe vpon their treſpas; Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dahs confeſſion of fault by ſham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> found glory: that none but ſuch a Iudah ſhall haue praiſe of God; and as Iohn the fourth vvas deareſt to Chriſt, ſo he to Iacob moſt glorious. All the reſt had theyr ſorovves for Ioſeph; vvhen ſome ſayd, come let vs kill him; as the Scribes, of Chriſt; &amp; Beniamin became Ben-ony a ſonne of Sorovv: For loſſe of his brother; &amp; printed his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovv in his ſonnes name: in Ros &amp; Bicrj, Gall &amp; biternes haue I for my Elder brother &amp; Ioſep vvas among his brethren ſold for Sicles by Iudas aduiſe to ſaue his life: bus Chriſt by Iudas to loſſe of life: Ioſeph in durance betvvixt tvvo, told the one of ſalvation, the other of death: ſo Chriſt told the one in durance
<pb facs="tcp:152051:22"/> with him, that on the right hand, of ioy: &amp; left the railer to pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſh with the ſcribes: &amp; the other rauers: that ſet their mouth againſt heauen. Briefly all the Patriarkes were biſhops for their families: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> vſing all care to teach theyrs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their fathers ſpech what Sem or Melchi-ſedek lerned of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſala taught of Adam, of the holy trinity: &amp; hovv Chriſt by death ſhould vanquiſh him that had the power of death. They wold not miſſe to Catechize their ſonnes in theſe poinctes: &amp; how our Lord ſhould come of Iuda: the king of glory, the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, the framer of the world, of that poor ſhepheard, to be a man: to haue his tabernakel in vs; to loke throvv the vvin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes within our wall. They did fede vpon his fleſh &amp; blood, comforted in ſorow by this hope. As Ioſeph gaue <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to fede his brethren. So all good Math. 25. giue <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to fede theyr families ſoules. In one vvord <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> never vſed afore but in Ioſeph vvith the 70. our Lord his gracious tongue cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs to the Patriarkes ſtory: to look to heauen, not vnto Thalmudiques Kingdome in the earth that God curſed. S. Mathevv requireth ſo much to be conſydered in theſe Patriar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes; to marke by induction through them all, the nature of the Kingdome of heauen. And for that vſe they are ſo particularly ſet dovvne. Othervviſe their pedegree vvas vvel knovven from other places. But Chriſt vvold haue vs to mark that theſe vvere the ſonnes of Adam in vvhom the Eternall vviſdome delited.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Phares</head>
               <p>Midras Rabba noteh vpon Geneſis, hovv God playd delite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vvith theſe ſonnes of Adam. Iacob vvas buſied in mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for Ioſeph, as being dead; Ioſeph vvas buſied in his afflicti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ones, the other Patriarches vvere buſied in theyr mariages, &amp; the bleſſed God vvas in diſpoſing counſel hovv Meſſias ſhould come of Thamar; of Thamar, a Chananean: of Thamar, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das daughter in lavv: of Thamar, by Iudah. Again Phares ſtri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ving to be borne before Zara, (vvho firſt ſtredched out his hand) hath his name of violence, ſhevving at his byrth that he
<pb facs="tcp:152051:23"/> vvold lay ſtrong hand vpon the Kindome of heauen; &amp; is a patren for all, as Iacob, to ſtriue for the Kingdome from yong yeres.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Ezron.</head>
               <p>Fzron is by interpretation the midde of Ioy; as Eron vvas borne at Iacobs going to Egypt; 215 after the promeſs &amp; 215. before the Paſcha. Iacob knevv that yeres 400 from Iſaacs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction vvhich vvas thirty after the promeſſe, Abrahams ſede ſhould come from Egypt; &amp; the promeſſe vvas 30 afore the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, vvhen Iſaac entred ſix yeres &amp; 55 after, Iacob is borne; vvhen Iſaac is 60. &amp; at 130 he goeth into Egypt ſo 215 vvere ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Chanaa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; &amp; Ezron vvas borne at the middle of their hope The notation of his name vvold haue lightened their darkenes vvho thought that the dvvelling of Iſrael vvhile they dvvelt in Fgypt, vvas 430. yeres. The meaning of the Ebrevv text is open in my concent &amp; aduertiſemen to; they that vvill, may fetch it thence. Wher I brought demonſtration that Moſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould be dead forty before the lavv, by Genebrard: vvho vvold haue Iſrael 430 yeres in Egypt. And I cited old Rabbines moo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then one, for 215 &amp; 215. as in my Ebrevv vvorke dedicated to Prince Maurice. That alſo I turned into Latin.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Aram And Aminadab.</head>
               <p>The immortality of the ſoule vvas taught by Abraham, Iſaac, &amp; Iacob, by ſpech of their peregrination; ſhevving hovv they vvere ſtrangers in Chanaan; &amp; loked for an heauenly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. So Ioſeph, ſvvearing his brethren to bring his bones from Egypt, ſhevved that he folovved Abrahams hope. And Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis ending in Ioſephs bones calleth all myndes to Ezekiels val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of bones, &amp; to the generall reſurrection. So Aram &amp; Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadab in theyr notation, teach the ſoules eternall happines; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram is high, as Iſrael baſe in Egypt, vvas high in hope of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. So Ammi My People Nadab is noble, loketh to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of the fathers from Adam to Noe; vvherin all faithfull are tvviſe noble. Diodorus Siculus commendeth Egyptianes
<pb facs="tcp:152051:23"/> for their reſolute opinion that Soules in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> had floriſhing ſoiles for the Godly; &amp; a priſon for the God leſſe. And Homer the Eldeſt, &amp; Plato, &amp; troupes, Elder &amp; later Grekes, are true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reported; to haue lerned that, from Egypt. Novv from Iſrael did the Egyptianes lerne the ſame. As our Lerned, Clemens, Euſebuis, Theodoret, &amp; vvho not, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> taught. And from the dayes of Aram &amp; Aminadab, the high and noble in Chriſt did the Egyptianes lerne, that, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as Plato ſayth. The ſoule aeides vnſene, goeth to the Aïdes, a place noble &amp; pure &amp; vnſene, vvith good iourney, to the good &amp; vviſe God. Novv the proud heathen trimmed them ſelfs vvith the oſtriches of Iſrael, all in mynd as Aram &amp; Aminadab in name. So vvhen the Romanes floriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed in lerning their beſt from Tully dovvne 300 yeres ſhevved ſmall reſolution for Soules immortality: vntill Chriſtianes in our Symbolon or note of faith taught the true foundation of a ſound common vveael; That the iuſt crucifyed to death vvent to the father, by the holy phraſe: to Haides by the heathen; vvher Abrahams boſome receaued the faithfull. Abrahams boſome in Haides, as Ioſephus or Ireneus, or Iuſtine Martyr, or Lerned Caius teach. For the vvork is fathered vpon all theſe. Iohn of Zorobabel &amp; other poor taught Luke of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch &amp; Theophilus the Soules immortallitye. And the Deuels at the laſt could not retaine theyr auctority for vviſdome but by the ſame philoſophie. Porphyry a frend of the Ievves, &amp; ioyning vvith Ioſephus for Haides to be the heauen for the godly: &amp; not ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vvhat our Crede ſpake, &amp; as good a Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian as euer could be, &amp; vvith the Deuels an enemy to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt, yet recorded from oracles that Chriſt vvent hence to heauen. His vvordes are vvorthey to be cited Thus the oracle ſpeaketh of Chriſt: Euſeb. Ap. 3.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:24"/>
               <p> That mans ſoule in Godlines paſſeth all ſoules; and the ſoule of the Godly goeth to the reſt of Heaven.</p>
               <p>In that place of Porphyrie Chriſt is called of the enemy Por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phyrie, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Godly &amp; a dvveller in the arches of Heaven. But he ſaid Chriſtianes vvere mad that held him a God: for he knevv not that God vvas in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And yf he had not knovven full vvell, that Plato vvold have made him ashamed, yf he had denyed, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Godly, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be a moſt happy paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to Heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he vvold not ſpared vvrangling vvith Chriſtianes, yf they had taken that article in anie other ſence, then this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute meaning, that all juſt goe hence to Heaven. In Cant. 6. 12, My ſoule hath ſet me in the chariotes of Ammi Nadib, my people the noble; So all Godly be Aminadab, as the laten tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation ſpeaketh; becauſe they teach Egyptianes, that the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Haides, be in Abrahams boſome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Naaſſon.</head>
               <p>Naaſſon hath a badge of faith in his name; that he should have EXPERIENCE hovv Iſrael should come from Egypte. So they loked to the very yeare vvhen their deliverance should be. As ſince Babel fell, they reckoned yere by yere, hovv nere they came to the kingdome of Chriſt. And vve should not be as Parrets, to regard the bare ſond of name, but to knovv vvhat the notation told.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Salmon.</head>
               <p>Salmon ſhevveth in his name that he ſhould come into the reſt of Chanaan. Naaſſon died in the vvildernes. But had great glory in the offringes: appointed firſt, as father of Chriſt. To Salmon Rachab vvas maried; vvho had greater faith then ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hundred thouſand of Iſrael; for ſhe beleued that God vvold giue Iſrael the La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Chanaan. S. Mathevv citeth for Rachab
<pb facs="tcp:152051:24"/> priuate recordes; as S. Paul had for him ſelf vp to Beniamin.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Booz.</head>
               <p>Booz cometh next; hauing a name fit for one that vvold be a piller in the hovvſe of God. By it Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> termeth one of the tvvo pillers; Boos, vvith ſtrength, Iachin, he vvill ſettle. Ruth vvas maried to him, aged as an Abraham: &amp; in Ruth leauing countrey, Kinſfolk &amp; fathers houſe, lot is reuiued, vvho folovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Abraham out of countrey, Kinſfolk, &amp; fathers houſe vvas felovv in the bleſſinge: by Ruth that did the like.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Obed.</head>
               <p>Of Booz &amp; Ruth cometh Obed, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a ſtay in old yeres, to Boos.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Ieſſaj.</head>
               <p>Of Obed cometh Ieſſaj. His name is ſubſtanciall; &amp; is hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably mentioned a father of Chriſt; the root of Ieſſaj. He had many valiant ſonnes; &amp; again Seruiah his daughter had valiant ſonnes; as Ioab &amp; Aſael.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Dauid.</head>
               <p>Novv Dauid is one moſt glorious. The letters of his make, Chriſt his name; BELOVED through Salomons ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. To him Chriſt is promiſed vvith an Eternall throne. That is; in the vvorld to come. 1. Chr. 17. He, vvhile he vvas afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, vvas godly; at reſt, he fell; in Vriah, &amp; Bathſeba; To be an example for all that ſhall beleue. And this much for the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral fathers of Chriſt; al, teachers in theyr cariage, of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. And Bathſeba the adultereſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> rarely Godly in the end, is a grandmother of Chriſt; celebrated in the pſalme of repertance. 51. &amp; pro. 31 &amp; all prophetes are in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me of heauen. Lu. 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the Kinges that vvere not fathers to Chriſt.</head>
               <p>Salomon &amp; his brother Nathan vvere ſonnes of Dauid, by Bathſheba; But knovvledge of the holy trinity, &amp; of Chriſt his incarnation &amp; reſurrection made them the beſt ſoules. And
<pb facs="tcp:152051:25"/> all vvho blame them for ſodain in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mities, &amp; commend the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not for their heauenly vertues, ſhall not be of Chriſt his bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren. Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glorifyed God in his infirnite vviſdome; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing thinges viſible to ſhevv the vnviſible of God; his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall povver &amp; God head; &amp; ſpeketh of the Eternall ſonne Prov<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. hovv his delite is in the holy ſonnes of Adam: as he gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his peoples ſtate in a moſt pleaſant frame: that the blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt may ſee a clear provocation of all to ſalvation. His grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> povver, &amp; building of tovvnes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuffred not his hart to reſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the night; &amp; his vvomen only overravvght him: to ſuffre, &amp; by his charges to build, Idole places; vvher upon he ſavv that Gods threat vvold overthrovv his Kingdome; &amp; before, he knevv from Moyſes, Deut. 28. that the Kingdome ſhould be overthrovven; &amp; that in a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge countrey Iuda vvold pray loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king tovvard the temple Leu. 16. 1 k. 8. &amp; God vvold hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them. And vvhen by his practiſe ſuffring Idolatry, he occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the renting of his Kingdome; &amp; foreſavv deſtruction <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f temple, city, comon vveale he vvriteth his Goſpell, That al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnder the ſonne is vain, &amp; the Kingdome of Chriſt is not of this vvorld; but the promeſſe of the Eternall throne to Dauid, vvas for the vvorld to come, that vve, ſhould loke for the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> iudgement. Herod ſhould moſt carefully haue lerned this much; vvhen he firſt lerned the ſtory of Salomon. vvho vvas the firſt &amp; laſt that had all this vvorld at vvill; to ſhevv that Chriſt his Kingdome is not of this vvorld. And yet this day the Ievves look for a pompous Kingdome; as I haue layd dovvne theyr vvordes, in Ebrevv &amp; Engliſh, to Eccleſiaſtes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And Salomons caſe alone might haue taught Herod, Pilate, Ceſars &amp; conciſion that the Pompe of this vvorld is not fit to brede povertie in ſpirite; to brede morning, to brede mekenes, to brede hunger &amp; thirſt for iuſtice, to find the Kingdome of heauen vvhen the vvhole fovvertene pilgromes in this vvorld folovving heauen in a quiet priuate hope could not move He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,
<pb facs="tcp:152051:25"/> all being our Lordes fathers, &amp; all beſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſtate, the firſt turning aſide fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his liue noble in the vanity of this world, &amp; leauing no hope for others to com nere, ſhould haue vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that 'the King eternall vnviſible bleſſeth men only to his vnviſible Kingdome that is not of this vvorlds. So Herod had not Killed the yong children; nor had come to ſuch an horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble death as Ioſephus recorded, to haue ſhevved an entrance to his Eternal flames: becauſe he vvold knovv vvhat the Angel &amp; Daniel taught the Perſian ſages for the Kindome of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Roboam.</head>
               <p>Roboam being forty vvhen his father vvas fifty tvvo; as Ievves vniverſally &amp; old Grekes from them do gather his who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le life, might vvell be knovven of Salomon, &amp; touched in Kohe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th or eccleſiaſtes vvhether he vvold be a vviſeman or a foole. A foole he ſone proved: &amp; could not rule that vvhich his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers gate &amp; mainteyned by greate care. And his mother Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah the Ammonite vvas not like Ruth the Moabite. And vve ſhould not hope for both Lots daughters to be rare; vvithout ſpeciall vvarning from God. Novv Roboam vvas vexed by vvar from Ieroboam all his time; &amp; left for Herod a vvarning that Chriſt his Kingdome ſhould not be like his; &amp; that the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Perſia came not by Daniels Chronicle to look for ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kinge. Abia his ſonne is vvell coupled vvith him, to giue vvarning of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Abia</head>
               <p>Abia vvalked in all the vvayes of Roboam: a ſecond vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Herod that Salomons houſe vvold not be vpright vvith God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Aſa Ioſaphat &amp; the reſt</head>
               <p>Aſa good, yet impriſoned the Prophet, a Pope father or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop from God; as yf he had impriſoned Chriſt him ſelf. Ioſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat a good King made bad affinity vvith Achabs houſe that Ioram ſhould mary Achabs Daughter. Iezabels alſo she might vvell be. Athalia is the vvoman. Another Iezabel. Hence Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram
<pb facs="tcp:152051:26"/> killeth his brethren his ovvne bovvelles: &amp; his Moth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Iezabel, as vvell she might be, killed the prophetes; &amp; the lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſome muckhil, that her name ſoundeth, dreamed to kill the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes and chariot of Iſrael: Elias the nevv Enoch. Then folovv exemples for Herode; to knovv matters to come, by former notoriours. Tvvo &amp; forty yeres Omries houſe vvas a plage to Iſrael; &amp; ochozias King of Iuda aged 22. vvhen his father died at forty, in the firſt yere of his regne, fell by partaking vvith Omries houſe againſt Iehu, fell to be Ben, in the giltines of the forty &amp; tvvo yeres. Eſra cunning in Ebrevv, vvhen he pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Chronicles, littel thought that men vvold be ſo barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as to make him aged 42. &amp; tvvo yeres Elder then his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vvhom the propre ſtory of the Kinges vvritten by Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, made aged 22. for the ſame yere. Ezra a repeaters, pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the ſtory eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, of one caught in the giltines of the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>milie ſo long vvicked &amp; caught in theyr ſin; in the tvvo &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth yere. The ſpirite vvhich beautified the heauens, vvold haue the ſtory beautified vvith Eloquent Ebrevv, that they ſhould be Barbarous that vvold not mark this to the bottom. Novv Herod might ſee in Athalia fit Motherhood for Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paters ſonne. Such a vvife vvas fit to be Herodes mother. &amp; Herod might knovv by her end vvhat his ovvne vvold be. And any might ſee that a Kingdom geuen ouer by God to the ſvvord of Athalia, vvas not of that throne vvhich God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to Dauid to ſtand for euer. Athalia Deſtroyed all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of Roboams mother the ammonitilh, that might be Kinge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for her children by a former Huſband; except Ioas vvhom his aunt ſaued, being an yere old Who is called of God ſix time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at the leſt for propriety ſonne to ochozias; a miſerable ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a miſerable father. Ioas the Cain killed the Prophet zacharie that prophecied of Chriſt his Kingdome: killed him, betvvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the alter &amp; the temple; vvher none but ſacrificers might come; The vvight moſt vnthankfull, &amp; Gods hated killed him vvho ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> father by his vvife ſaued his life. Herod might ſee &amp; the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees
<pb facs="tcp:152051:26"/> might ſee them ſelues the ſonnes of this Cain Ioas; vvhen they vvold ſhed blood ſpeaking more forcible then Abels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Touching a forged Table, pretending to reconcile S. Mat. and S. Luke, bringing Ioas &amp; all after him to be holy-Fathers &amp; our Lordes <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; attributing folly vnto the Eternal wiſdome of God, to bring the moſt holy, of the moſt wicked: I gave advertiſement, &amp; as I here, through Britany, it is wel taken. Other countreys alſo have it: I wold wish them alſo to marke theſe short speaches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They, vvho vuold make the Apoſtles to teach all Thalmu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diſtes, that they ſinned, holding Ioas and all after him, to be of Salomon; and not to be holy men in S. Luke, termed by other names; paſſe Machmad infinitely in all extremity of impuden<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty: and Lucian the Dog vvold ſay, the vvheſton vvas vvonne from his true ſtory; by them vvho vuold feigne tvvelue men together, to be Kinges of tvvo names; and the one kind neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eard by the learned of that nation. I hope D. B. vvil hold this true at the laſt: and vvho could euer haue thought, that reaſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable vvightes vvold euer print or buy ſuch a Table. And the miſerie of the familie, might teach Herod, that Chriſts his Kingdome vuas not like theyrs. Wher Ochoſias, Ioas, Amaſi as, vvere all three ſent up to Haides by bloody death, to give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt before Cods Throne, of theyr Sceptre; and the pleading ther at judgement vuold be as tolerable for the Kinges of Acab by father, as for them, thence by mother; and S. Mat. leaueth them out, as a ſhame to be named in Salomons hovvſe; &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vvorthy of reckoning in the Nevv Teſtament. And here he tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth Herod and all, by ſilence, more then any by anie cries, that none heauenly mynded, vuold bring Chriſt the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch, or from ſuch a Kingdome, ſince Dauid vvrote; <hi>Thy Thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, o God, is for ever &amp; ever: the Sceptre of thy Kingdome, is a Sce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptre of righteouſnes: thou loveſt iuſtice, and hateſt ſin. Therfore it is
<pb facs="tcp:152051:27"/> moſt evident, that God thy God hath annointed thee with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yle of gladnes above thy felowes.</hi> Yet in the ſixt generation from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cab the vvicked, King Azarias found mercy; aged 4 yeres vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Father vvas kild; and vvas ruled by the Councell, about 12 yeres; and ſo ſomvvhat better brought up, then yf he had bene ruled by his Father. Yet he dyed in a Leproſie, for offring in the Sacrificers office, in Chriſt his Kingdome; in vvhich of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice Sem the great by the name of Melchiſedek, vvas deſcribed a Sacrificer in phraſe ſtill abiding, as ſtill alive. Azarias ſhould have lerned that of his Father David; &amp; that none of Iuda vver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to come nere the altar. By Lavv death vvas the payment for the action: for endeuour a Leproſie brake out in his forehead: vnto his death ſhut up from comon companie. And by this puniſhment of Salomons hovvſe, Thalmudiques ſhould have lerned, that Chriſt ſhould be a King in an higher perſon &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; as the Eternal, the brightneſſ of glory; having all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God in him; vvho carieth about all thinges by his migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty vvord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; by himſelf performing a clenſing ranſome of our ſinnes, ſhould ſit on the right hand of God. Vnto ſuch a King Herod &amp; the Scribes might hav looked, &amp; to an Eternal thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. And in this age God shevved a shaking of Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s houſe. In the yere that Vzias died, the glorie of Chriſt fil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, vvith a ſmoke of anger; &amp; the poſts of it trembled by the terrible earthquake, mentioned by Zacharie; at vvhich the people fled. Then Eſay ſeeth Seraphin in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple; Angels repreſenting the Chaldeans vvhic shall burne the temple; &amp; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> taught of ten calamities to come afor the laſt deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; vvhich I haue ordered in tables in my Concent. Theſe terrours made Ioatham a good King: but Achaz vvold not beleue, as did Eue, that the Sonne of God vvold be a man of a virgin. He had be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vvel plagued by Pekath; &amp; his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vver kiled by the Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes. Ezchias vvas a good King; but after deliuerance from Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib famous in Herodotus, he shevved the Chaldean his vvelth; as hauing ſome truſt in it; &amp; is told that his poſteritie
<pb facs="tcp:152051:27"/> (by daughters) shal ſerue in Babels court. Manaſſes that ſavved Eſay, ſavv all ſin &amp; ſlauerie; Amon vvas ſone killed; holy Ioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, for vvicked ſubjectes vvas killed: Ioachas died in priſon: Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>akim vvas captiued<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and caſt avvaie unburied; Iechonias vvas kept. yeres 37 in cloſſe priſon. Sedekias eies vvere polled out. And his children vvere killed; &amp; the ſtate felt Ieremies Lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ations. And novv let us come to the third fovvertene.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Who made the third fowrtene;</head>
               <p>Theſe be the third 14; Salathiel; Zorobabel, Abihud, Eliakim, Azor, Sadok, Achim, Elihud, Eleazar, Matthan, Iacob, Ioſeph, Mary, IESVS<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Theſe be called the holy of the moſt high Tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie. Dan. 7 The Chaldean golden head vvas beaten to duſt, the tree had the axe ſet to the root, the Lion vvas caſt into fyre, for afflicting theſe. So vvere uſed the armes &amp; breſt of ſiluer, the Beare in the trobled ſea, the Ram, of Madai &amp; Pares; for not tendering this familie; ſo the Grecianes vvhole in Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der &amp; his ſonnes; ſone rooted out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> came to nothing, for Tyrannie o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer the nation vvher theſe should have bene honored. So the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olemies in Egypt, the ſouth to Iudea, and Seleucidae of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyria north, both chalenging Iudah, &amp; fighting ſtil vvith du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble campes in Iuda, ſo waſting it, periſhed for injuries unto the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe. Theſe Grekes whole &amp; parted wereall the Image after the breſt &amp; armes. The Leopard &amp; the fourth beaſt, &amp; the whole Buck. And ſeaven times be every one of theſe ſet furth in the Prophecy of Daniel. The gracious Prophet ſo deſcribing the afflictions of the third fourtene. And Ieſus in Daniel cha. 2. is the ſtone which beateth the great image into duſt, one like the Sonne of God. Chap. 3 one like the Sonne of man coming in the cloudes: chap. 7. Meſſias, or Chriſt, the holineſſ of all holineſſ. Chap. 9 Michael chap. 10 &amp; 12. And the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet D. should be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared with this laſt 14: touching, Herod Ievves &amp; Ceſars, that the Kingd. of Chr. is not of this world.
<pb facs="tcp:152051:28"/> And the vvhole booke which I Ebrevved for Ievves, goeth u<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon the houſe of David, and chiefly toucheth theſe laſt four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene; and may profitably be joined to the Commentarie upon the Parcels of theſe tvuo Euangeliſtes. And this much for them; profitable, as I deme, for all ſtudie touching our Lords Familie. Certen further helpes ſhalbe added as tyme ſerueth. But thus endeth the explicationes of both Euangeliſtes, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Lordes Fathers and Predeceſſours in right of Kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Poſitiones explicative of matter tow ched brieflie, and firſt againſt the ſlander of Iſaak Ben Arama; ſayng untrulie, <hi>That our Gospell teacheth that the Patriarkes had no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the perfection of ioy; but were in Hell, and that Chriſt went thither to redeeme them. Thus he writeth vpon Levit. 26. fol. 205 of the Venice Edition.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The firſt occaſion of the Iewes fall; and the harme that cometh by it;</p>
               <p>SAINT Paul speaking of the old faithfull, hath ben miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſtianes, ſome, for theſe vvordes; ch. XI. V. laſt. <hi>All theſe, glorious by faith, receaved not the promeſs: God providing ſomwhat better for us: that they should not have the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes without us.</hi> It is euident through the vvhole Epiſtle, that the Apoſtle disputeth on this; That the Fathers vvere taught
<pb facs="tcp:152051:28"/> in the old time, of Chriſt by the Prophetes; in ſundrie maners; but at the fulnes of time, he spake by the Son, that God made him Heyre of all; by vvhom he made the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orldes. But ſome Chriſtianes thought he spake not of doctrine; but of joy to the Faithfull ſoules gone hence; that the old Faithfull had not the joyes of Heauen at the firſt. Vpon that, the Ievves inferre that vve taught the Patriarkes vvent to Hell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Yf they vvent not to Heauen. And that could not be true, that Abraham and Moyſes, ſo familier vvith God in hovvſes of klay, should not haue grerter familiaritie after their ſoules vvere freed from the corrupt bodie. This errour of Chryſoſtomes upon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Heb. XI. the Ievves uexed.</p>
               <p>Euer ſince Chryſoſtome uexed them for Dan. 12; and limi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted times for affliction under Antiochus; and limited for yeres 400. Gen. 15; and yeres 70 under Babel; and ſo 490; Dan. 9. under Heathen. So that God had limited time of hope. Ben Arama cited an old vvork named Siphry; vvho uexeth us novv a thouſand yeres; whence Machmad might feyn righter keyes of Paradiſe; and ſtrenghten Arrianiſme: as Arius, in Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius; that yf Chriſt vvent to Haides, He had not the higheſt joy. And thus Ievves help Machmad, by miſtakers of S. Paul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>the 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> occaſion:</head>
               <p>To this day the Ievves continue the ſlaunder by the Crede; ill tranſlated through all nationes; and badly expounded to di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſturbance of all Faith. To aunſvver them vve muſt shevv that by the Nevv Teſtament, our Lord and all juſt vvent hence to Paradiſe; as the Church did alvvayes expound the ſcripture; &amp; the Crede.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>the Church of Englands faith:</head>
               <p>Firſt England ſhalbe cleared, vvhich allovveth and comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:152051:29"/> the R. R. F. Th. Bilſom Biſhop for his ſermon: wher he handleth ſcripture &amp; Fathers: &amp; proveth by both, that our L. went hence to the high joy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>D. Bilſons profe by ſcripture from his ſermon fol: 219</head>
               <p>We haue no warrant in the vvord of God to faſten Chriſts ſoule to Hel, for the time of his death, that he vvent not hence to Paradiſe to the unſpeakeable joy of the Faithfull: Thus the R. R. F. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended for one of the beſt of England; ſhevveth that all auctoritie vvil, that all faithfull vve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hence to Paradiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And yf anie Ievv ſay, Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d holdeth faith vvithout ſcripture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nabal is his name, and Nab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la his fame for folly haunts him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; for a foole vve vvill taunt him:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>An other vnuincible profe brought <hi>on from Luc 16, for the terme Haides, which in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams &amp; Eleazars ioy, is a feaſting</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Thus from D. Bilſons vvordes a full ſyllogiſme may be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: of truth unvincible;</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Yf our Goſpel place Abraham in Haides in joy, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vvicked in torment, Haides muſt conteine Paradiſe for Abraham, as Gehenna for the vvicked.</item>
                  <item>Novv, as Ioſephus, ſo S. Luke, makes Abraham boſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Haides: &amp; the place of torment: on high both; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all Ievves confeſſion in Cether Malcuth fol. XI</item>
                  <item>Therefore D. Bilſon proueth Ben Arama to be a ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derer; and himſelf a R, R, F.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>A ſecond ſyllogiſme often printed, breaking all Europe. a work of Iohn Cant. &amp; Th. Winton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The place vvhich receaued our L: ſoule vvas Haides of the Crede, Ioh; Cant; and all Grekes:</p>
               <p>Paradiſe receaved our L; ſoule, Th; winton, Lavv, &amp; Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, &amp; the old Grekes &amp; late reformed Churches.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:29"/>
               <p>Therfore blaſphemous Ievves may ſee they ſlaunder us; &amp; vve conclude plainlie, the ſound in Divinitie &amp; tongues as the BB. &amp; Nobles of England, BB. in their place by the ſcripture tongue, vve conclude, that Paradiſe is the Haides of the crede; &amp; Ben Arama ſlaundereth, teaching that the Chriſtian church ever beleved our Lord vvent to Gehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na. Never vvent he ſaith the Church, ſo beleved vve, that he neuer vvent; but vvent to Paradiſe. And thus our R. R. FF hau made a ſyllogiſme of high eſteeme: that moved all Chriſtendom to yeld vnto them The rareſt in Fraunce, novv ten full yeres ſince L; W: made Paules tremble at his ſyllogiſme, honour and celebrate this concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; That the barbarous tranſlation, to deſcend to Hell mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in learned ſpech, fitted unto the moſt eloquent Greke of the Crede, plain to all Grek countreis, a going vp to heaven. The rareſt in Holland, the floure of Leyden, folovv our Eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Biſhops, Other in policy, Bishops of good calling; The beſt of Friſia, Weſtphalia, Steinford, and floure of ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in Marpurge, and the vvhole Churches in Francfurd, and the learned of Hanavv, and the rareſt in Eidelberg, vvhoſe let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters be at Hanavv, yeld vnto our Eccleſiaſticall and Politicall Bishops: teaching or allovving this concluſion; And the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours in Geneva ſpake to the penner of this ſyllogiſme; vpon demaund vvhat our Bishops thought of their; D: Beza and ſuch, vpon avvſvver ſayd, Deus benedicat tuis ſtudiis; Damus tibi licentiam imprimendi quicquid voles: Alſo Nicol; Serari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us a principal Ieſuite, being thriſe demaunded, vvhat should be aunſvvered for Pope to Ievv: thriſe vvrote: the Pope never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued that our Lord ever vvent to vvorſe lodging then the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes had; vvher Athan. Baſil, Cyrillus, Theod; place them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:30"/> who in all their vviſe thoughtes place them in the higheſt joy for men: upon Davids Pſalmes: Baſil vpon Pſal. 15 in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume. The other in fragmentes printed by Commelin; and ſo ſay the beſt Diuines in Theophyl. upon Luc 23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>of Athanaſius ſeming to differ;</head>
               <p>Becauſe Athanaſius ſaith of our Lords Reſurrection <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſome thought, that Porters of Hell vvere here meant, but they are deceaved. For the vvordes being of the lxx. Iob 38. can meane no more then doth the Ebrevv there mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne. And thus goeth the Ebrevv in the vvordes of God to Iob. cha. 38, 16; Haue the gates of death bene reuealed unto thee? Or haſt thou ſeene the gates of the shadovv of death? The te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath no more nor leſſe then this. And this later is Greked as I cited. The levv vvhich tranſlated Iob, vvas excelent in Poetry; &amp; by veres might be Prophets ſcholer: to Aggay and Zachary, &amp; knovv that Chriſt might tell Iob thus; Thou haſt not ſeene the ſtate of the dead; but in manhood I vvill breake theſe bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res; by a reſurrection that shall neuer again ſee death: as sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the poſtes of that hovvſe. So Athanaſ. amazeth none ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned. And thus Athanaſius ſtriueth not vvith the ſyllogiſme of the R. R. F. vvhen judgement in Ebrevv &amp; Greke is uſed; O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thervviſe a Ievv, or one bent to help Machmad for nevv keie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Paradiſe, might find a trap to himſelf, and to as vviſe as him ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But none, that can call the Greke Father to the lxx, &amp; the lxx unto the Ebrevv, vvilbe anie vvhit moued. And if anie Alexandrean Ievv or Machmadiſt toke offence at Athanaſius to brede nevv keies of Paradiſe in despit of our Goſpel, he hath felt judgement. Athanaſius ſaing, that our Lord vvent to Hai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, neuer meaneth that part of Haides vvhich is Hell, but that part vvhich the faithfull held; vvhom he placed in high joy. Whither yf he had not gone, our ſoules should never come to
<pb facs="tcp:152051:30"/> their bodies. And ſo all the Greke Fathers aunſvver Arrianes, objecting as a baſenes the going to Haides; vvher yet the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoules be, as the moſt lerned Photius ſpeaketh in Oecume<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nius, upon 1 Cor. 15. One D. ignorant of that, ſpared a truth to the K. of three Kingdomes; for vvant of ſurveyng Hell as aright. But yet he joined to the making of a good ſyllogiſme, the beſt vvork that euer vvas made by our Bishops, the beſt to ſtop vvicked ſlaunders of Ievves for Machmad, againſt the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell. And all expoſitiones of the Crede out of this ſence betray not onlie the Greke Fathers; vvhom yf Ievv and Turk foile, all is gone, but betray alſo the Goſpel; vvhich vvill not be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Hell-forget tormentes, rooting out all auctority of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie, of Ebrevv, of Greke, of conſcience in ſpeach.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>of a thyrd ſyllogiſme; which <hi>the ſurveyer in an Enthymeme made vnto the King.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The uſual Greke muſt be holden the Credes meaning <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: to Catelthein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Haidou in the Godly, is a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to heaven by uſual Greke. Therfore a paſſage to Heauen is meant by the Crede. Ih. Whitg. rightly held Rhodaneanes ſenſeles, that embraced not the Propoſition.</p>
               <p>And B. Winton in ſecond thought ſurveyd that by the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes the phraſe meant the ſoules comon lot: to have diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the qualitie of the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; Parad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe Haides light for the good; Tartarus darkenes for the other. For the aſſumption, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the K. 145 Greke Epigrammes from all ſortes of Grekes in An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hologie: vvher all countreys and ages ſhevv vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formitie. And ſo three ſyllogiſmes, the R. R. F. hath made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Ben Aramas ſlaunder; Syllogiſmes all vnvincible, yee though, he himſelf vvold goe about to ouerthrovv them, he neuer could; they be ſo fortified; for Geneveans good; yf they had one drop of thankfulnes to accept it.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:31"/>
               <p>I mentioned Scripture, to prove going hence to heauen; &amp; that Abraham, Iſaac and Iacob &amp; all faithfull be there; but I hold all Britanes rude, that knovv not ſo much; yet the ſimple may take theſe; Mat. 8, Luc 13, Iohn 5, Luc 23, 2 Cor 5. 1, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared vvith Lev. 26 10, Heb. 11, vvher Abraham deſired the heauenly citie; and God had prepared it for him, and Eb. 9 &amp; 10. I cited in my reply againſt a Patroclean dreame, and vvorſe then Patroclean, for he feared not, but deſired Hades. And novv I nede not cite mo places. Reaſon vvold tell, that all uſe litle reaſon, that reaſon not thus; ſeing the Apoſtles infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly cite of our Lords death and reſurrection, and neuer have one ſyllable of going to Hell; they be of infinite impiety and contempt of God, that dare vvrite of a going to Hell; ſeing no Prophet repeateth a former matter; but vvith ſome change, yf the matter ſuffred anie more to be ſpoken. So all theſe repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be ſtained, by the unlearned vightes, that honour Hell a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt all Gods vviſdome; and againſt Chriſt his vvordes, that ſix times in one ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith, I goe vnto the Father; Who vvold euer think that Chriſtianes should ſo contemne God; or Scho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers be ſo barbarous, or men ſo ſenſeles. Novv becauſe the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeles barbarouſnes pretendeth English cuſtome from Davus in the marked take Poſitiones for the terme deſcending; &amp; the terme Hell; then I vvill returne to the Greke Fathers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of tvvo vvordes, Deſcending &amp; Hell, hovv the unlearned &amp; unſtayd do turne aſide.</head>
               <p>The termes Deſcending &amp; Aſcending are vſually taken for paſſages: vvher the ungrounded barbarous ignorant of vſuall ſpeach, make ship vvrach of faith. By theſe particularitez they may be inſtructed.</p>
               <p>Deſcending to Egypt, Gen; 262; and Ioſeph Hurad vvas cauſed to deſcend to Egypt, that is in our Church Bible: Ioſeph vvas brouhht to Egypt; Gen: 37; So Iuda vvent from his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; Ebrevv Iarad: Deſcended; And ſo infinitly in Geneſis for paſſage to Egypt</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:31"/>
               <p>And uſuallie in Ioſuae borders of land reching or going fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tovvne to tovvne, are ſaid to deſcend:</p>
               <p>And it vvold vvearie one to reckon the Iudges or defenders phraſe of Deſcending, for going to an exploit;</p>
               <p>In Samuel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Kinges and all the ſtories, Deſcend is the vſuall paſſage; and ſo Aſcend; as Anabaſis expeditio Cyri.</p>
               <p>Some time it is tranſlated <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to goe, by the lxx, Gen. 43 5, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Sam. 294. To go, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to paſſ through. And in double active; to cauſe to deſcend up the Arke; that is, to carie it. And the lxx tranſlate it; to aſcend Ruth 3 3 Io. 13. So Ievves and Ievv like may be aunſvvered: that the terme De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending is plain for anie paſſage; and al paſſage of ſoules he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is aſcending Koheleth, or Eccleſ. 3. for they returne to God, Eccl. 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is uſed in the ſame ſence, for paſſage from Nazareth to Capernaum; paſſage to Samaria, Cyprus, Seleucia Ceſaria Antioch, from Macedonia: likevviſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Suidas; for paſſage avvay. So ſcripture should muſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>underous Ievves &amp; Ievv-like barbarous. For the other vvord Haides is knovven to milliones in Britanie; and both together heard for 3000 ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res uſe to meane a paſſage of ſoule to God: &amp; in our Soile they are holden barbarous unlerned, that daregape againſt this. Shortly Germanie vvill ſo ſtop Ievves railinges, the vvicked helpers of Machmad. Let us marke Hades in the Nevv Teſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Now of the woord Haides <hi>or Hades, Hell in comon ſenſe, but never for to particular, Gehenna.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The R. R F. cited thriſe vvher God vvrote Gehenna, Mat. 5, tvviſe, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oonce; in al theſe places, he cited Hades, as though it had ben ther<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not regarding the Teſt. vvhich God gave us: but making a nevv from his ovvne vviſe head.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:32"/>
               <p>Yet all humane recordes, all together, all laid in a balance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are to S. Mathevves thriſe Gehenna, leſſe then the duſt of a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance. The true terme Gehenna, being a Thalmudique terme for ſoules place, confirmeth the Ievves comon place, vvho moſt learnedly teach, that the Ebrevv neuer nameth place of joy properlie; or of torment. Thus both are taught, Lev. 26. Yf you kepe my commaundements, I vvill dvvell amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt you. In Paradiſe, ſaith the Rabbin; by a borovved ſpech from Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s garden. Yf ye kepe not my Lavves, my angry face ſhalbe upon you, Wher? before the throne of God, and the Lamb, Apoc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. on high. Cether Malcuth; as the Ievves in proprietie of ſpech expreſſ their mind. For their Midras or fabling comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taries, they have a rule; that none may ſtay upon them. And he that cited them ſhevved in fevv vvordes, that he vvas a babe in judgement. When the Zohar agreeth vvith the Nevv Teſt: then it is certen old ſage, not late diſcanters bred the ſpech. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben Ezra checketh mightily the comon Midras; and comonly and notably Pref: to Moſes; The valley of Hernnon nere Ieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem vvas a place vvher children vvere offred to Deuels; bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to death; And the old holy Rabbines borovved that terme, to expreſſe Eternal torment; and our Lord confirmeth that, and their judgement therin, for all their vein in the Lavv; &amp; layng that dovvne once, tvviſe, thriſe, he teach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h all learned, to kep that terme in all tranſlationes. All bodies ſhalbe caſt to Haides; for it is the grave to the bodie; the miſerable bodies only ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be caſt into Gehenna ſo the R. R. F. vvold by Greke of his ovvne making haue marred all faith.</p>
               <p>To forged textes I nede not to aunſwer. The Pentheus in Euripid., that ſeeth a double Thebes &amp; a double Sunne, ſavv one; but this Pentheus ſeeth none. But vvhere Haides is in dede, he ſhalbe aunſvvered. The builders on the rock vvere not hindered by the gates of Haides. They feared not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the paſſe to the grave, death, and region of ſoules, as A thanaſius ſpeaketh. Capernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i Hades is in Ebrevv Abne Bor;
<pb facs="tcp:152051:32"/> the ſtones or clods of the pit; vvher bodies vvithout life lye, a child might ſone ſee ſo much Ebrevv &amp; Greke; and Scheol for building tentes cattels and mens bodies num. 16 had no vvorſe. A ſound Divine vvill not ſay, that all men dead there, died the ſecond death. Abrahams Hades, I often handled. That in 1 Cor 15 nothing helpeth the vvicked; ther for bodies it is the poiſon of Rottednes; Keteb a plagy ayer; Pſ. 91, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kabon. Rottednes ar centron ſting in the lxx, the comon ſting of the body: and Hades to the body is but grave and death. And ther Hades to the ſoule, as the moſt learned Photius in Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menius teacheth, conteyneth all faithfull ſoules vntill the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. wicked and barbarous vvrangling vvith Scripture bredeth fevvell for Hell. Death and Hades vvherof Chriſt hath the keys, as the Rabines ſpeak, should not take Iohn before the time, as Arethas ſaith Ap. 1. Hades that receaved Ceſares and their troupes, had bene no nevves to the ſerpentes ſede to be ſoules Hell; a gulf of buriall vvas there meant. When the ſea and Hades geueth up the deade, the grave, and ayer as Origen and Methodius think, yeld the bodies. Andreas ſaith truly, though leſſe fitly for a viſion; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The place vvhich receaveth our ſoules is Hades, there the vvicked are Death and Hades, Apoc. 20, as Arethas lernedly expoundeth the place; and they are caſt into the Sea of fyer &amp; Brimſton &amp; ſecond death. Elihu vvas not bolder to ſay: Men of hart vvold ſpeake as he; then the penner here; that Grecianes and Ebricianes, ſound from childhood, vvill ſpeake as he; that Haides is neuer hell in the Nevv Teſtament. But their tongues are ſet on fyer from Gehenna, that ſo teach; Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den properly to meane Gehenna Hell, either ther or in the Crede. None can deliver his ſoule from hell, Pſ. 89. all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhall deliuer their ſoules from Gehenna. So our Bibles ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er meane hell of torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: but vvhen Gehenna is in the Greke. Neuer in all the old teſtament; but by conſequent; that death to all the vvicked, comonly an haſted Scheol, or hades, hath
<pb facs="tcp:152051:33"/> Gods-hated in Hades the place of torment. An this much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpech of Dauis in the market for the true meaning of Deſcending &amp; Hell. Now let vs go to learned Euſeb. wher Haides is moſt nobly handled &amp; by B. Winton for Geneva: wher they could not help them ſelues. And now the R. R. F. his auctoures will confirme for poor Geneva all that theyr hartes can deſire: &amp; more then wicked Ievves vviſh to ſtop theyr vncleane mouthes foming out theyr ovvne ſhame, as ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging vvaues of the ſea. Lyers &amp; railers againſt all honeſty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Euſebius hovv B. vvinton citeth him: ſo that he might ſtop Ievves vncleane mouth.</head>
               <p>Euſebius is cired by L. vvinton, ſpeaking thus Eccl. hiſt. lib. 1. Cap. 13. He raiſed the longe layd in ſlepe; &amp; brake the vvall, that never vvas broken afore. Here the raiſed be the iuſt: &amp; from Haides: &amp; the difference is; that theyr bodies never more returned to Haides. That is meant by breaking the vvall vnbroken till then. Here Ben Arama might be ſayd to haue a braſen hard face, yf he vvold gather a going to Hell, or the long dead to haue bene raiſed thence: they gather vvell &amp; truly, that the ſoules vvere raiſed to theyr bodies from that part of Haides vnto vvhich our Lord vvent. But becauſe all heathen ſhould tell vvhat Euſebius ſhould meane: &amp; they vvold ſay he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant heauen by Haides: &amp; Euſebius doth ſo expound him ſelf; B<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vvinton might tell Ben Arama, that Euſcbius vvold tell Siph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i &amp; the Alcoran, that they greatly iniuried the Goſpel; to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hell vvher heauen is plainly meant. And herein B. vvin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton fighteth for England &amp; Geneveans, &amp; theyr partakers, that the old iuſt, &amp; our Lord, vvent to Hades vvhere Paradiſe Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Genevea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vviſh Grekes for that; &amp; the BB. of England cite auctoures that vvill ſuffre no other meaning for their vvordes, And the right referend fathers ſhould be the skumme &amp; ſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the vvorld, yf any Ievv Lerned in Ebrevv &amp; Greke, as all ought to be checkers of Biſhops, yf he could prove they meant hell, vvher the Auctours meant heauen. perverting
<pb facs="tcp:152051:33"/> ſo groſly, &amp; ſo croſly for to make their Hell from Euſebius Ecc. Hiſt 1. 13. vvho meaneth heauen Apod. 3. in handling the ſame matter by other termes. So Euſebius doth expound him ſelf; that all might be Heſiodean old ſucklinges that ſhould miſtake him. Alſo B. vvinton might prove that Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius meaned as Ievves for ſoules place by Citing the Ievv Ariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tobulus, The Peripatetique as agreing vvith Chriſtianes, &amp; ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting heathen poetes of our mind: in praepar. Euangel. li. 13. fol. 401. in theſe vvordes.</p>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The ſum is; from Empedocles in Ari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtob. The Ievv allovved by Euſeb. ſaith; the Godly going he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce are happie vvith divine vvightes in the ſame dvvelling. Thus the Athean Ievv vvas a lyer &amp; a railer againſt all duty by B. W. that blaphemeth us, in teaching that the holy vvent to hell.</p>
               <p>So Euſebius, B. vvintons auctour being ſoundly expounded ſtoppeth Ievves mouthes; &amp; teacheth, that Chriſtanes haue Ievves &amp; Grekes for them; that the good departing hence are vvith the happieſt. And Euſebius vvas to make good to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, the judgment of Chriſtianes in comon plain agreement; &amp; not to be a vvicked ſophiſter ſpeaking as to the heathen ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie; &amp; yet having on thing ready in his tongue: &amp; an other thing hid in his heart. A Ievv, or vvorſe then a Ievv ſhould he be that vvold then peruert Euſebius ſeing he teacheth ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the godlies going to Hades meaneth in Ievves phraſe; an adioining unto the Fathers; vvher they are equales to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, as Philo ſpeaketh of Abraham; hovv <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. No Chriſtian chec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth Philo for this. But ſome had, yf they vvere of an other mind and durſt combat. Therfore Ievvee should hold the beſt</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:34"/>
               <head>of Gregorie Nazianzen for tartaros <hi>and Catachthonia: wherein Epiphanius &amp; Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillus, &amp; S. Paul Phil. 2 be expounded.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Yf anie Buzantian and Ievv, angry that Chryſoſtome drove them there to ſhame, vvol be reuenged alſo of Gregorie Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzene, vviſhed to be Biſhop of Conſtantines Citie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in great election, vvold quarell vvith him for Tartarus, or Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tachtonia, in vvhich vvord Cyrill of Ieruſalem folovveth him, vvith Epiphanius, or upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> S. Pauls vvord <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, aunſvver is readie. Theſe auctours, vvhich meant that our Lord vvent hence unto the happie, are cited by B. Winton, for the right meaning of the crede; vvho expreſlie telleth, that no ſcripture denieth the going hence to Paradiſe, in ſer. fol. 219, often ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and in manie vvorkes, vvhich may ſtop the uncleane mou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes of Ievves. Novv they ſhallbe expounded, hovv they no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing help Machmades frendes for better keys of Paradiſe S. Paul ſaith, that in the name of Chriſt all knee ſhall bovv, of them in Heauen, or Angels, of them on earth, or the living here, or the lodged in the earth, of the dvvellers in heaven, or men liuing, no doubt can ariſe. The Thalmudiques celebrate infinitely, the high familie and the Lavv familie; and to their maner S Paul ſpeaketh. So becauſe the Pſalme 22 entitled the morning ſtarre, as D. Kimchi moſt lernedl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e expounds the He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brevv title in Ail, doth ſpeake of the morning ſtarre, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of reſurrection, S. Paul in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame argument vvold hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>venlie touch the phraſe. The phraſe vvent thus. Before him all that deſcend into the duſt ſhall bovv the knee. And none (other) can quicken his ſoule. Before he had ſaid, all the endes of the earth ſhall vvorship him; And the Angels are knovven for their vvorship Pſ; 97, &amp; Eb; 1; So S; Paul ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th no nevv matter; but ſpeaketh of the dead, as the Pſalme: and Eſa 26 19 of them that dvvell in the duſt: vvho <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or by a short ſpech, from the bodie are vvholy called, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the dvv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers
<pb facs="tcp:152051:34"/> in the earth; as in the heate, in Homer cited by B. vvinton. Eſays ſpech for this place muſt be remembred. Thy dead ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be made aliue; my carcaſes ſhal ariſe. Avvak &amp; reioiee yea that ſlepe in the duſt. Novv as the Angels are called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>So</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> be the men dead; or in heathen Phraſe the comon Haides as Nazian. ſpeake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h vpon Coheleth. 3. vvhoſe vvordes I cited; hov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ther the faithful reſt in ioy: as heathen vvold ſpeake. And therin he expoundeth the other tvvo fathers ſaing that our Lord vvent <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And Cyril of Alexandria is evident vpon the pſalmes, to meane that all the holy vvent hence to Kingly tabernacles. And Nazianzen being as one ſoule vvith Baſil, vvold meane in this comon place, as Baſil meant vvho teacheth vpon pſ. 15. that Dauid &amp; the old iuſt vvent hence to Gods holy hill as Mamony tract Poenit in the end bringeth the Ievves comon opinion; &amp; he vvas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he conningeſt in the Ievves affaires of all that euer they had, Moſes Mamonides: that Ben Arama vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of him the comon ſaing; Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moyſes to Moyſes, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e like to Moyſes. And this great Egle as they terme him, ſerching all the termes that in the Hebrevv touched Gehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na, yet durſt not bring ſcheol for any. The citers o of Midraſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, ſpeaking to memory of phraſes as one c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Midras Tillin for le Sheola ad Scheol vſque, that Scheol is ther Gehenna, ſuch in fevv vvords may ſhevv great vnſkilfulnes in Rabbique ſtudies. And this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch for Grekes againſt Ben Arama; from thoſe Grekes by vvhich the lerned father. B. Th. vvinton proueth moſt ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Geneva, that vvhich he affirmed, ſoundly: That our Lord vvent hence to Paradiſe. And no Ievv ever d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſt ſay, that any old Chriſtian thought of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ourney from Paradiſe to Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henna; or of going to Haides after the body vvas buried. Leſſe thought of triumphing ther over Devels; or that Deuels are yet tormented <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of an other Iudaique poinct.</head>
               <p>A Ievv of Amſteldam named Rabbi Dauid Farar, a revolted
<pb facs="tcp:152051:35"/> Chriſtian, as of late I have ben informed, and as it ſemeth, for he is readie in our I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in ſcholmen, and a great ſercher of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantages, by our ouerſightes, vvas ſavvvd in hart, vvhen he ſavv my Ebrevv Catechiſme for R. Abr. Ruben: wherin Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans Prophecie to Dauid, vvas deriued from Dauid, not by Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lomon, vvhoſe houſe, Ammonean, &amp; Achabeam came to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ine; but by Nathan Salomons brother, 1 Chron. 3. 5, vvo, vvas <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Father in the flesh, to the Sonne Eternall: vvho then vvas in his loines. This ouerthrevv all Ievves hope: vvich upon Eccleſiaſtes I shevved to be a spiders vvebd. He vvas fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther greueth, vvhen I gaue him my Latin Concent: vvherin he ſavv S. Mathevv, not a Publican, but a moſt eloquent Lavv<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ier; vvho in Kinges ſpech, maketh the ſucceſſour, So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne; though the predeceſſour died vvithout children: as Achab is Sonne to Baaſa; no kind to him, 1 <hi>K.</hi> 20; and Sedekias Sonne to his bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers ſon, yonger three yeres then himſelfes. So Salathiel the heire, exceding far off, vvas ſonne, in Lavviers phraſe, as Iuli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an, to Romulus, in Caeſarib. This greued the ſcholeman Ievv. For he thought a longe time to haue vvon the ſpurres here; to proue that our Goſpel could not be of God: vvher Salathiel &amp; Zorobabel should haue Fathers up to Salomon by Iechonias, &amp; up to Nathan by Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i and Melchi: and he vvas ſure to oue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throvv the Goſpel, againſt all, that graunte, that Iechonias had naturallie children. For they vvho here faile, bring ruine to the narration. In the which, if anie lie or falshood be found; all the hope of life is gone. Our traitours, vvil not marke that; but the enemies doe obſerve it: and dravv revolters. The heaven might be aſtonished, hovv the Doctours of the Lavv could be blind: on Ieremie 22, all ſavv, that Gods decree paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth abſolutelie upon Iechonias, that he should die childleſſe. Maimonie ſaw that, tom. 1. tract. Poenit. as in a common pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce to all conſent: Ialcut noteth Gods oths paſſed; which Moſes repentance could not call back being paſſed: all note this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Yet the Ievv ſeing my reſiſtance, and the Dutch of his mind, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:152051:35"/> that I vvold giue him leaue to reply on me an vvhole af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er none in open audience; I vvas content; the place vvas appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; a Great colledge hall vvas appointed; &amp; many vvillingly met: I gaue him the vpper end of a long table, and I took the nether; and vvrote all his reply; that non ſhould giue fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port: experience taught me that. For vvher, I once defended the Greke, Act. 13, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er a ſort 450 yeres; to be pure in letter, againſt Rhemiſts rejecting the Greke, and folovving the Latin, vvherby Pope or vve, loſt the ground; and vvere vvicked in our foundations; an ungrateful Libeller, brutish for vvant of lerning, cauterized for conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vvold be winning the whetſton, writting that I defended the lxx; whom all learned, theſe 1300 yeres, knevv to haue i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite milliones of faultes; and I, who made a nevv Greke tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation, should be thought to knovv ſo much, ſo well as another; and no wit could tell to what concluſion Papiſtes and I should theri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtriue. But wher our ſide graunted the Pope, that ether, the N. Teſtament was corrupt, or Dauid neuer borne, wherbie Pope and Iew fell the Goſpell; I de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ended, that wee had a pure N. Teſtament, and the Remiſtes modeſtlie told, that none of their, ſpake ill of me, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lucianes or Iulianes.</p>
               <p>In memorie of this I wrote the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewes argumentes, and ſtill made him wearie by plaine aunſweares, and to flee t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtill; &amp; then he touched other poinctes, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Daniels Image in E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſebius meaning, worſe then Iudaique; and Daniels ſeauens, in the Thalmudique meaning; and priuatelie ſince, the text of the N. Teſtament. Wherin if I haue no more thankes then of the libeller for the yeres of the Iudges, my labour wil bring labour upon labour. This much I wish all to weigh, that we muſt de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fend not onelie the Hebrevv text to be pure, but alſo the Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u T. &amp; our hartes might blede to ſee our p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uishnes to help <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es to hold the ceremonies neuer ended; and to place Eaſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Weſt, &amp; precedent tokens going before the incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to folouu <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or the daies of Chriſt his flesh.
<pb facs="tcp:152051:36"/> Of theſe I vvill vvrite alitle for Amſteldam &amp; the portugalles, &amp; our Iſcariotes, vvho for 30 ſicles vvold ſell Machmadean notes vvith the Bible.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the fourth Monarchy.</head>
               <p>He at the firſt vvold haue Syrianes, Perſians, Grekes, &amp; Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes. But being vvarned hovv ſo he left out the Chaldeanes, denyng all the Prophetes, left Euſebius in that poinct: vvher in all Ievves held the trueth: &amp; cometh to the fourth King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: vvherin ſince, he hath vvritten in Latin a treatiſe to me &amp; againſt me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Thus reaſoned D. Farar.</head>
               <p>Yf the fourth Kingdome, vvhich muſt be duſt in the image befor God of heauen his Kingdome is ſet vp, yf this Kingdome be the Romanes, yee miſtake the true Chriſt</p>
               <p>But the fourth Kingdome is the Romanes.</p>
               <p>Therfore the true Chriſt is not yet come</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Br.</head>
               <p>I denie the aſſumption; The fourth Kingdom is not the Romanes; But the parted Macedonianes; a parted Kingdome from the third; &amp; called one in reſpect of clayming Iuda, to both ſides; &amp; by ioyning mariages ſtill, Syria vvith Egypt; &amp; the Romanes had bene vnfitly figured by tvvo legges being one Kingdome. Beſides the mariages together had bene no diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiones. For all nationes mary vvithin them ſelues. But the mariages of Seleucidae &amp; Lagidae paſſ al in all ſtories; continued nere 300 yeres handled in many vvriters, Strabo, Appiane, Pauſanias, Livi Trogus, &amp; moo full many. Beſides the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes had made the inages legges longer then the gyant Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoeas vvhom Iuppiter buryed in Tinacria vvhoſe head vvas vnter one mout; &amp; his tvvo feet reached vnto the other. But Gods providence contriued all to a fit proportion of a mans body. The Chaldean of ſhort time to haue a ſhort part; 70 ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. the Perſianes in breſt &amp; ſhoulders to let dovvne the armes 130. nere double to the other Alexander &amp; his captaines ſone
<pb facs="tcp:152051:36"/> deſtroyng one another 23 beſide Seleucidae &amp; Lagidas, to belly &amp; as ſo many ribbes: &amp; all ſone cutt off to haue the ſhortnes of a belly: &amp; the reaſon is plain, that Alexander vvas to be ſone cut off; becauſe he vvold be a God, proud by ſucceſſe; And a Poet vvold ſay, he ſhould be cut off leaſt he vvold make vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res for heauen. Novv the tvvo legges vvhich continued dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Perſian time; &amp; in mariage; that Cybioſactes a ſuppoſed Seleucides maried the late Gleopatra theſe haue a fit proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; &amp;, ſtrong a vvhile, are thick thyghes: vveaker are the ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer legges; And vvhen Antiochus Epiphanes ruled Egypt &amp; Syria, Gyges Aſia, &amp; Egypt, &amp; Phayt or Phaytons Lybia, as Ezekiel told. Ch. 38 &amp; 39. &amp; Polychronius the Greke vvhom I gaue you vvith porphyrie &amp; other Grecianes, doth him &amp; theſe matters rightly handle: vvhen Epiphanes ruled both; then the tvvo vvere one Kingdome; &amp; for vvarning touching his altering of the lavv, the viſiones vvere chiefly ſhevved; &amp; Ch. 7. 8. 11, &amp; 12. agree to the parted Macedonians to every vvord of Daniel; &amp; your expounders confeſſe that the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Epiphanes vvhole rage is of dayes 2300<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; Rabbag ſayeth that the legges conteine the ſame matter; &amp; that the Kinges of the north &amp; ſouth Ch. XI are the tvvo legges; &amp; for Ch. 12. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus ſayth as Daniel, that he held Ieruſalem three yeres &amp; an half; &amp; your Machabees note that ſone after (at a month) his army ſmarted; &amp; ſone he (after dayes 45) fell by Gods hand. And heathen ſtories agree to Euery ſvl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able; vvhich by chaunſe could not fal out one vvord by chaunſe may fal fit to a matter not purpoſed; But as an hog may dig the letter A, vvith the no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, yet cannot dig Andromachaes vvork of Ennius; ſo heathen could never fit Seleucidas &amp; lagidas to every vvhit of Daniel vvhom they never ſavv, but that God cloſly ruled the Balami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to teach Iſrael. Moreover it is moſt ſenſeles to think that the Macedonians vexing your nation, vvith double campes in your nation; eating as vvith teeth of iron; for fiue Kinges of one ſide &amp; fiue of an other, &amp; treading all dovvne by campes
<pb facs="tcp:152051:37"/> vvhich they coul not eate; it is moſt ſenſeleſs in you to think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that no prophecy ſhould tell you of theſe poinctes, but 300 ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſhould be paſſed over; &amp; Turke, &amp; Caeſar, &amp; ſouth Kinges late in Aben ezra vpon Dan. ſhould be meaned. Gehenna i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtly devoureth your natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as fevvell ready for it, that deſpiſe Gods goodnes, leading you ſo clearly by Daniel vnto Chriſt his birth, by the Image; &amp; vnto his death by Aben ezraes vvordes Dan. 9. That ſeauenty ſeauens of yeres are from Daniels prayer to Seale the Meſſias the holynes of all holyneſſe. And doth not this ſpeake as vve, that God vvas in Chriſt reconciling the vvorld vnto him ſelf; vvho in death overcame him vvhich had the povver of death; &amp; the vvorld vvas ſubiect to the ſon of Enos, a litle inferiour to Angels by ſuffring death, but Crovvned vvith glory, by reſurrection &amp; aſcention. To vvhat ſonne of Enos could the vvorld be ſubiect being a bare man? vvhat bare man durſt the Angels vvorſhip at his coming into the vvorld: by pſ. 97. &amp; Kimchi confeſſeth that to be ſpoken of Meſſias coming into the vvorld. And Sadaias vpon Dan. 7. confeſſeth Meſſias the ſonne of man coming into the vvorld; &amp; ſitting vpon the right hand of God by pſ. 110 And vvher your Thalmud denyeth that vpon pſ. 110 Iarky &amp; Aben ezra cannot agree. But Iarki vvith Sadaias vpon Dan. 7. ſay Meſſias is ther meant; &amp; the perſon ther ſone returneth to the Euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: &amp; thence ruleth all Kingdomes: coming into the vvorld as ſone as the Romanes tribute ſhevved that the Macedonianes the fourth Kingdome had not one tovvne of governement vnder the cope of heauen. And hovv can you be ſaued deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſo great ſalvation; vvhich telleth by ſo many ſtories in Daniel; yf this &amp; this for 500 yeres fall out as vvas foretold lok for the redemer in the yere that Aben ezra told; &amp; to be Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>as &amp; the moſt holy by Aben ezra: &amp; to ſit on Gods right hand by Rabbi Sadaias. Thus ye may ſe that not the Romanes but the Macedonianes vvere to be the deſtroyed, before Chriſt came into the vvorld. And you might rede vvhat a gracious
<pb facs="tcp:152051:37"/> commentarie the N. Teſtament maketh vpon this poinct; yf you haue any vvorde to gainſay ſpeak on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Farar the Iewe.</head>
               <p>None but you &amp; D. Iunius make the parted Macedonianes the fourth Kingdome M. Plancius &amp; the Preachers of this tovvne are againſt you for Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hovvſe, for Daniels Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle, for the Crede, &amp; for the fourth Kingdome; &amp; hold not the nevv T. to be pure in text. And the BB. of England be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you in their notes vpon the Bible for the fiue poinctes; &amp; ſpecially that yee haue no Nevv Teſtament from God. For they vvrite plainly vpon many places, that your teſtament is moſt corrupt; Ievves of vs vnderſtand Engliſh; &amp; Beza far paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in that: him in latin I can rede.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Broughton.</head>
               <p>Of all I haue vvrirten yonger then novv by 20 yeres; &amp; combaters yeld; therfore, doe not oppreſs me by them vvho reiect them. But for the preſent Queſtion of Kingdome, you iniurie many. Not Iunius only but alſo Tremelius, &amp; all Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva in there laſt Bible, &amp; D. Piſcator a very learned man, &amp; D. Polanus, after that I came to Baſil, as once he yelded for Dan. 9. but revolted again to the groſer Olympiades, all theſe ſtand to me for the legges; &amp; many in dutch Homilies, &amp; Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtes after Bodinus full many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; tvvo very lerned of Bretany; &amp; no B. of England that the Prince of the nation made B euer deſpiſed my book of Conce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; &amp; many Britanes &amp; others think that none vvold; but ſome one counted the ſkum and ſcomme of the vvorld.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:38"/>
               <p>The Ieſuites of Mentz humanelie confeſſed, that they vvold graunt all that book; and long agoe by tvvo Cardinales adviſe, vvold haue moued me to haue taken a principal Cardinalship; ſayng, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t I might do much good to the Church, yf I had a Prince that fauored my ſtudies; and I told them, I hoped I had: all theſe I muſt defend againſt you. A Bishop in ſyrname, bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t certen bookes of mine, hindring his gaines for notes upon the Bible, damned of old. But of him I complained to the Lordes; ſo B; Cot; exc. brent bookes comme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nded by the K<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; Arch. VVh.; moſt highlie a litle afore his death; and others againſt you; vvhich none but a Ievv in hart or errour, vvold hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: and complaint vvas made to the Lords againſt him; and ſome promiſed to moue the K. for a verie great ſtipend to teach you Ievves in Ebrevv. And for the Bishops of England, none of the Princes making, or vnlothed deadlie as enemie to the Bretish nation vvill thank you, forſayng onlie D. Iunius is vvith me. Milliones of milliones through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urop vvold shevv, they agree vvith me. As you maie think Polychronius and enemie Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyrie haue bred milliones novv manie ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es. Thus your cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of teſtimonie is aunſvvered, as untrue: &amp; here your Iev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es vvhom you lead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Gehenna, should knovv by one crime, all your trecherie; and vvhat a Sinon you are. You knovv Virgil, &amp; as Sinon, <hi>Incendia miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, ridentem dicere veru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Quid vetat?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>DAVID THE IEW. I will write a book in Latin; that aunſwer you in print. <hi>BR.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>As the Thracian modeſtlie prouoked me in Ebrevv, ſo ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vvill I aunſvver, from Rabbines ovvne syllables. To turne your nation, &amp; you ſeeme little modeſt to call me to combat vvith you in Latin; vvith you, vvhom milliones of our yonge
<pb facs="tcp:152051:38"/> men could breake. I told you ſadly that you ſpake many vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, for fevv. But never one vviſe to my hearing. But your vvork ſhalbe printed, ſend it me. And this much for our diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, vvhich occaſioned all the former booke. A book he ſent vvhich Hidelberge hath to avvnſvvear, or to ſhrink.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the Angels determining Clearly vvhen Moyſes lavves ſhould be buried, by the burial of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>I tranſlated the Angel Gabriels ſpech into English, as cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectlie, yf manie be not deceaued, as anie hath done into anie tongue; omitting no letter of aduantage, for the clearnes of Chrsſtianitie; nor vvreſting anie vvhit; that a Ievv might ſay I vvas partial in a Grammer cauſe; and ſome thankfull DD. of Oxford thought it dutie, to tell others: that I tranſlated the An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gel ſpech, better then anie before me. Yet, ſome R. R. F. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovved M. Livelie to tranſlate ridiculouſlie, Ievvishſlie, &amp; dead lie; and to raue againſt me, being at the Alpes farr off, in Zuit zerland; vvho to my face, neuer durſt hold himſelf my equall: but hath bene often blamed of me, for extreme vvant of judge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, in Ebrevv; Arch. Wh. cannot be blamed: for, M. Liue lie told a Bohemian, felovv in vvagin for Cambridg, that he vvrote againſt Beroaldus and me. But the Arch. shevved no countenance to him; but all of high diſcontent. For heatheniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in the Perſian Kinges he ſhevved him ſenſeles, to aſtoniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the laſt propheticall bookes; Daniel, Ezra, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henias, Eſther, Agges, Zachary. And his commender ſhevved him ſelf moſt vvicked, &amp; vnlerned extremely to aſtoniſhment: &amp; impudent extremely to athean madnes; that vvold foyle the biſhops rightly folovving the Ebrevv text; For, To Seale ſin: though the margent haue; To Finiſh. Readinges are 848 in the Ebrevv; vvher the text, &amp; the margent are both pure: &amp; the margent checketh not the text, as corrupted in Babylon; but
<pb facs="tcp:152051:39"/> both text and margent are from God. Arias Montanus hath made an whole work of textes, as corrupted; and ſo Plantines great Bible is printed in deede corrupted. For this I have bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Arias of extreme ouerſight: otherwiſe the man was of ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re learning; but for ſcripture tongues; I feare not to cenſure him. And I have shewed in Helue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia, Marpurg, and Mentz, the reaſon of the double reading, &amp; none euer before me, from Iewes teſtimonies, or plain reaſon. The commender of a foi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of our BB. ſo referend, and ſo learned as the libeller him ſelf commendeth them to be, should be counted a brainſick foole: &amp; receave into his owne boſome, all the vilenie of his libel. who the partie may be, that determine I not. But all will determin, that he was a shameles aſſe: that wheras the Bishops held the right: the Line word, allways the ſafe, and not chect, but expounded by the margent: and ſo proteſt in word, that our nation holdeth not the text corrupt, in none of the 848 margent readinges (for they are all of one auctoritie;) he wold ſtain the ſagenes of our BB. &amp; commend a blaſphemer eight hundreth forty eight fold, of the pure text: which, yf we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray, the ſcripture may not judge controverſies; as a corrupt judge, but Rome, clayming to be the Church, muſt judge, as not erring. This Lonchios the blind Knight, that can perce the ſcripture to the hart, with his prophane ſpeare, shall ſee what he hath perced: &amp; the diſgracer of the BB. wher they better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, then in all their deſertes, this Lonchios should be eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as a blind Bayard; &amp; no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e should for this, gev him honour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Farar the Iew.</head>
               <p>Farar the Iew, that openlie in a Colldge Hall at Amſterdam, as I told, diſputed vpon Daniel to diſgrace Chriſtianes: yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer durſt blame our BB. for tranſlating the text. But the libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler is more Iewish then anie Iew, to diſgrace the BB. &amp; ſtealeth their auctoritie, to prove, that they miſſed of the Bibles words; Yf a ſtraunger had ſo condemned them; namely that they knew not what the Bible was: theyr pleading had bene eaſier.
<pb facs="tcp:152051:39"/> But now a creper into their boſome, damneth them by their owne auctoritie; to make them befoole themſelves, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they deſerued rarelie well, 848 times wel: by honoring one place, that draweth al of the kind 847 with it. So the hart of the foole was on the left hand. And herein he is Iew is her in rancour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſtian good, then anie rancourous Iew. In theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poinctes, the Iew is equall and a felow And the Iewes damne him in the former; but in the folowing, he joineth with the Athean dogges.</p>
               <p n="1">1 In denial, that our Lordes ſupper ended the lawfulnes of ſacrificing. M. Livelies wordes I cited in my advertiſement; how he held ſacrifice lawful in Veſpaſianes times; So the Iewes hold, and none moo; but M. Livelies commender. So Farrar the Iew, &amp; they, be equallie enemies to Chriſtian faith. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianes think, that our Lordes death ended ſacrifice &amp; offring; and we celebrate our Lordes ſupper, as a ſeale, that our Lord ended Moſes ſacrifice; when he went through the veile of his fleſh into the holy, to find eternal redemption. Both theſe the libeller denyeth; he denyeth that he went hence from the croſ into heaven; and holdeth ſacrifice lawfullie continued; as did M. Liuelie; the firſt he did, commending Patrocles.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Farar the Iew denyeth, that 490 yeres juſt, were from Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niels prayer, vnto the ſealing of Chriſt. So doth M. Livelie: &amp; his commender. More Iewiſh then Aben Ezra; who being an enemie, as well lerned as ever was enemie vnto Chriſtianes; yet proteſteth this to be moſt certen (as I touched afore, and often may profitablie;) that the ſeaventie ſeavens are, from Daniels prayer, vnto the ſealing of Chriſt the holie of holie. His ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables I haue expreſſed in copies Ebrew, Greke, Latin, Engliſh; in copies, above ten thouſand and the beſt lerned in Chriſten dome haue in print ſhewed thankes; But M. Livelie &amp; his libel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler wold be more Iewiſh then Aben Ezra: and not cite Iewes for Chriſt; but folow Iewes againſt Chriſt: and likewiſe alſo a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt all Chriſtianes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:40"/>
               <head>Of the name Meſſias twiſe in Daniel <hi>Ch. 9. meaning Chriſt properly, &amp; vndeniably.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Vherſoeuer the name Chriſt is in all the Nevv Teſtament, it calleth the reder to returne vnto Daniel, ſpecially the tvvo places, vvher Meſſias, the Fbrevv vvord, is in Greke letters; &amp; that in the mouth of ſimple folk; as Andrevv the fiſher; &amp; the Samaritane vvomans, ſhevving that the Samaritanes then as all he Ievves, knevv vvhen Chriſt ſhould come into the vvorld. M. liuely denyeth Meſſias in the Angels tongue, to ſound the redemer. Thirty yeres agoe I checked him, ſpeaking ſo, ſayng that he ſhould be forced to alter his mynd. And then he ſayd: he v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>old not ſtand in his opinion. Yet finding a commender, he returneth to agree vvith the baſeſt of the faithles Ievves, to greue all Chriſtian mindes, for euery place of the nevv Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vvhich ſtill calleth vs vnto the holy name Meſſias, or Chriſt: &amp; vnto the holy miniſtring ſpirit the Angel Gabriel: from vvhoſe doctrine, vve are called Chriſtianes. So the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of M. liuely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> returned to God, ſhould plead of force, vvhy he commandeth a joyner vvith the groſſeſt athean Ievves; vvher their better lerned vvold be aſhamed to Croſſ Gods vvord: but in one place or other, vvold ſhevv that Daniel ſpake of Meſſias; vvhich vvord vvas never ſimply pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre before the Angel ſpak it. So his commender commendeth layng an axe in a lunatique phantaſy, to the rote of the tree of life <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Deutero. 32. 2 &amp; Pet. 2. And this much for the Ievv Farar; to vvhoſe hate of Chriſt, Iſcariot Liueliſequa ioyneth, vvho the party is, I vvill not reſolutely affirme. The Biſhops, vvhoſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritie he drevv, to countenance Iudaiſme, ſhould find him out; as their deadlieſt fo: &amp; a blaſphemer vvith the Ievv Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar. God Killed the printer of the libell: againſt the ſcottiſh miſt; &amp; yf milliones haue not payd for it, the plague &amp; deluge
<pb facs="tcp:152051:40"/> payd. And God called, afore Liuely, the ſtationer, charge man of printing liuelea. Let all mark hovv God vvill deale vvith the vvounder of all the Bible; vvounder of the holy name of Chriſt; &amp; ſtayner of the auctoritie of Chriſtianitie: a vvonder to be extolled in a common vveale of Chriſtianity. And this much for Farar, &amp; Liueli ſequa yoked together for infidelitie of Heatheniſme in Liueleis &amp; his commender, &amp; vvorſe then He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atheniſme, in madnes, putting tvvo Kinges betvvixt good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tax; &amp; him ſelf, &amp; cutting of him into Kinges tvvo; and of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Cimmerian darknes for Ezra vvith Nehemias; of theſe I haue giuen aduertiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t elſvvher. And becauſe the defender hath no lerning to defend him; &amp; Athean railing framed from his ovvne cariage, vvill not novv ſerve, vvhen the miſt is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a ſun: &amp; he can never avvnſvver to one poinct of a thouſand of his errours: &amp; madnes, it is better to leaue him to the iudgement of God &amp; the King; vvhile the party may be miſtaken, then to preſſ him further. But ſome think the levv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh vvell knovve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> For one &amp; the ſame vvork, telleth that one &amp; the ſame man four times ſkophed the ſcottiſh miſt; vvhen the Nero hoped to ſee his ovvne cuntrey on a flame; &amp; ioyned vvith Ben Aram for Hell; vvher D. Bilſon proved moſt ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially that as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in African us &amp; Euſeb. Apod. 8 fol. 242 is the Ievves going vp, as the ſcripture ſpeaks, from Babel to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. So it is, for our Lord to go vp from the Croſſ to Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams Haides; vvhence me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould think of revenge &amp; the ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is auctour of both equaly bad doctrines A noble of Scotland noted fovver times vvith vermilio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſcoph; &amp; milliones novv note the poiſon of his hereſie; though D. Bi. vvrite to the King only of tvvo, having forgotten him ſelf in his vnvincible ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme to be a third. But vviſdome vvill make all yeld vnto obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience tovvard King &amp; Goſpell; &amp; cover much miſchieff. Yf God meane not to pluck avvay all Biſhops landes; vvhich yf it be vvithdravven, both vniverſities vvilbe cold. Biſhops in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſo far paſſing tvventy vicares in learning, as in revenues, vvold make our nation the glory of all Kingdomes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:41"/>
               <head>Of M. liuelies skill in Iudaiſme to <hi>tranſlate againſt Chriſtianitie; &amp; what learning a tranſlatour should have.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I requeſt the gentle reader to mark M. Livelies skill in Ebt. and mine; by both our tranſlationes of Gabriels wordes Dan. 9. Yf God ſent me &amp; lent me anie judgement, M. Livelie u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed litle; and his commender as much. In the advertiſement, both our skill may be tryed, of him &amp; his learned defendour, I will diſpute no more. His tranſlation vvill ſhevv agrement vvith Iudaiſme; and fight againſt all Chriſtianes; and here for all, I vvill lay dovvne a fevv rules; to shevv vvhat learning a tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſlator ſhould haue, for Ebrevv and Greke: and for all artes, to judge of Equiuocationes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Ebrew.</head>
               <p n="1">1 He muſt knovv that the letres Ebrevv, the 22 vvhich vve have, vvere not invented by Ezra; as manie fabled, but giuen in the Tables to Moyſes, and knovven of old.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Greke Alphabet, vvhich deuided Homers Iliad &amp; Odyſſea, is elder much then that age; of Babels captiuitie; &amp; it is named from the Ebrevv; and the Ebrevv much elder then it; and the Characters that gaue the name, yet much elder; and ordered in the Alphabet, for like forme; and ſo ordered in the Pſalmes Prov. 31; and ſix times Lam. in all, 21 times; therfore an Ebrician vvold not be found Analphabetus, to learne his, A, B, C.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In Noas time Podamim &amp; Dodamim; Piphath and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phath. Thubal and Chalyb by tranſpoſition, noted the letters to be of old as this day; and manie countreis in Heathen na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from Noes familie; differing by miſtaking letters. David Kimchi noteth manie ſuch 1 Chr.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The lxxii, had old dimme copies; as 1000 yeres old, or more; wher theyr eies often miſſed, by letters like; as yet they be. D. Druſ. noted that vvell in Ciun &amp; Rempham; a tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of courage vvold put Ciun Act. 7. from Amos 5.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:41"/>5. Vovvels had Gods auctority in the tables; as Tiphereth Iſrael teacheth. Their infinite varietie could not be from man; &amp; no mans auctority could prevaile to force a nation to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake them; yf the prophetes in all ages had not ſettled them, as theyr age ſpake.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Accentes haue vſe to ſtay ſpech by the argument; as De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes excelled by pronuntiation. I brevv accentes teach that to Ebrevves: &amp; that, not Muſique, is theyr vſe.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Elias Leuita doted vvhen he denyed that any old gramma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rianes afore him of renovvne: ſayd, that vovvels vvere of old. kimchi vpon Hoſeas expreſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elleth, that Ionathan Coaeual to S. Pauls Rabbi, the ſage Gamaliel, had Hoſeas poincted.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Azarias blameth Elias; by that all nationes haue vovvels; then ſpecially Iſraell; more curious in ſtyle, then all Greke po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etes.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Tiphereth Iſrael ſayth ſagely, that all the lavv is now at this day vvith vs, in the 22. Letters in vovvels &amp; in accentes, as in Moſes time. The Pope, vvho beleued Elias, vvarring againſt them vvho ſay the poinctes, &amp; ſo the accentes are from God, the Pope beleving Elias, and vvekeninge the auctoritie of Gods vvord, herin dealeth not vvell: nor any of ours that fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv him. No mans vvit could invent 14 vovvels; vnleſſ at the firſt they had them; nor nedeleſſ variety of poinctes, to great difficulties of grammer, vnleſſ autours had vvritten ſo at the firſt. So Benj, my ſon, hoſeas 11 &amp; Math. 2. might as vvell be Banaj, my ſonnes. So Gnaſaj, God, my makers, for myſticall tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in Elihu, might as vvelbe Gnoſi, my maker. And ſeing Iewes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from Babel, as Iulius Africanus in Euſeb. Greketh, aſcending to Ieruſalem, folovved Arabians to haue vovvels, comon, as Mariam &amp; Miriam, Salomon, &amp; Solomon, Abel, &amp; Ebel, Gog, &amp; Gyg, Cores, &amp; Cyros, it vvas not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for late Ievves to perſuade one man to reſt in many late-in vented vovvels.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:42"/>10 Two kindes of Chananean Bibles we have now; vowel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and vnvowelled; ſo they had at the firſt. The one for cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentie, yf doubt came; the other for expedition. As we write vnvowelled. So R. Ruben to me; and I to him, in my late prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted workes. The lxx vſed only the vnvowelled; to hide with more facilitie, holy thinges from dogges; when danger was.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>What Auctours we have to help tranſlation in Hebrew.</head>
               <p>The Apoſtles tranſlate exceding much of the old teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, even as the lxx have done before them. So much muſt be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed: &amp; the harmony deliteth: and the Apoſtles Greke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, in notable places, migh be ſet profitably in the margent. Alſo the Apoſtles tranſlate much of themſelves. Therin they will be dull contemners of God, that follow not him. Wher A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtles tranſlate not, Arabiq Moſes, the Chaldy Paraphraſtes, and Thalmudiques in Moſes Chair, are good warrantes. Super intendans are ſlender in learning that are Babes in this kind. And knowledge <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> haumeth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which ſpent short life in longe diſcourſes, for matter wherin, all mindes know more then any tongue can tell. The incarnation and reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, how it hath ben folowed or contemned from the begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning: with civil plain cariage in Gods; and Satanean in the contrarie, this conteineth the ſumme: and they will lie againſt this infinitly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or ſpend their life in idle Ceremonies and heavy lawes, whoſe ſoules are not ſeaſonned, with the exact ſtyle of Gods word; Burſt with envy towards painfuller ſtudent; and as ſure to hav pay, returned upon their heades. More Academies of Alamanie then one wold ſone ſee theſe wordes juſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the New Teſtament.</head>
               <p>All the New Teſtament is penned from God in Greke. The
<pb facs="tcp:152051:42"/> Reporters that S. Math. vvrote in Ebrevv, or S. Paul to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brevve; neuer marked the Greke ſtyles of both in Attiq for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of ſpech, that Salem hath not. And the holie Ghoſt neuer tranſlated book; but kept ſtill the originall, of all that he vvold have tranſlated. Here be four Dialectes, the Attiq, Iudean. Thalmudiq, and Apoſtoliq. By ignorance of vvhich, much darknes covereth dealers vvith the N. Teſtament: as I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>victed one Doctor, to haue shevved ignorance of all theſe in one queſtion, ſo groſſe, that a man vvold marveile vvith vvhat face he durſt chalenge anie diſputation.</p>
               <p>Being cumbated,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Projicit ampullas, &amp; ſeſquipedalia verba.</head>
               <p>The vviſe man caſteth off Atti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> and vvhen Homers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter vvas cited for hard vvordes; he could not think of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarchus in old Didymos; but of late Euſtathius, as vvhom S. Peter could not reade; shevving yet therin all his learning; as though Euſtathius cited his ovvne; and not Heathen, elder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Machabees. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are the plague of quiet opening holie truth. Ignorance of Iudean Septuagint hath apeared ſtrange; vvhen he ſaid; Aey Sheol is Hades; and the Greke Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vnderſtood not the lxx. But S. Auguſtin had great skill. Forſooth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for erroneous Latin; <hi>Quinta generatione exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt ex Aegypto,</hi> droue him to a tedious diſputation. It is ſtrange, that a ſage man should ſpeak, ſo voide from the vvho le tenour of learning. And vvher S. Auguſtin knevv not vvhy the lxx added ſo manie hondred yeres, &amp; vvhy Mathuſala by them lived beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the flood; the blind vnthankfull vvight vvell might haue ſene that, handled firſt in England. And vvithout obſerving vvhat Ebrevv the Apoſtles tranſlate a nevv, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hear the dum ſtones Apoc. 21, tell all the old ſtory of both Teſtamentes; a matter precious, and better then all the Iev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the vvorld. Laſtlie, for ignorance of Thalmudiq: vvorld to come, or Haides, the vvorld of ſoules: he placeth hell in this vvorld; and vvold rob Grekes for the one part of Hades. Thal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudiques,
<pb facs="tcp:152051:43"/> compared vvith Attiques, had here holpen him. The Nevv Teſtamentes tranſlater should profitablie joine to the Greke, the Ebrevv, ſet to the lxx, or to their ovvne nevv tranſlation: and the Thalmudi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> to their phraſes; and note the Attiq by their auctours; and Thalmudiq: and joine an abſolute Table of all theſe; and regard all in Engliſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the Text purenes. <hi>Rabbi Farar.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your Nevv Teſtament is corrupted in text. And that your Preachers graunt; and ſome Amſteldamean Ievves haue dvvelt in London: and read Engliſh condemnation of the text; &amp; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za in Latin, often amendeth the text. Novv you vvill graunt, it is not of God, yf it be corrupted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Br.</head>
               <p>Much rancour is vttered in your fevv vvordes. Matters to have made you a Chriſtian, plain, is there; vvhich your vveak head might learne; and not put quarels as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to proue your ſelf full of poiſon, and voyd of lerning. I vvill for diſputation ſake, make my ſelf an enemie to the Lavv, &amp; thus reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvith you. Rabbi Farar vvill graunt, that yf the old Teſtament be corrupted, God gaue it not, and I am ſure it is true. For Gods Prouidence vvold kepe pure, all bookes that he vvold haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued; as vvhen Ieremie &amp; Ezra abridged manie bookes ned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les for all aages; thoſe God vvold not haue more copied; but left at the Ark, vvhich vvhen the Temple vvas brent, could not eſcape: or othervviſe, God vvold haue to decay. But Ieremies Kinges, &amp; Eſraes Chronicles, to be kept to euerie letter. Yet I, as an enemie vvill thus diſpute.</p>
               <p>Yf in Carui Pſ. 22, for Caru, all ye Ievves, have corrupted all copies this 600 yeres againſt the Maſſoreth, &amp; haue in Dan. 8 Chaldean Kings name prophane vvith ſhin afore Aleph in this notation; Bel enricheth, &amp; not as ch. 7 vvith Aleph afore Shin; Bel giues a fire of vvoe: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Maſſoreth vvarneth; yf all you herefolovv corru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ption,
<pb facs="tcp:152051:43"/> God gaue not the Lavv; or you are vvicked;</p>
               <p>But all eyes may ſee vvhat you doe:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Therfore by you God gaue not the Lavv.</head>
               <p>Novv Rabby Farrar, vvhat yf a Turk thus diſputed vvith you: vvold you not be turned into a ſtone as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or, in vvordes unvviſe, of Hecate God vvold ſtir diligence: &amp; I dare defend the copies pure Pſal. 22 &amp; Dan. 8. But I cannot defend your troupes. So you ſhould not object unto me our troupes. You haue my Latin Concent; ther you ſee my judgement; that the Bible is ſettled all as one bodie; pure, clear, &amp; perfect; Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, Sonnes Incarnation, and Aſſumption to Heauens, is the Diuinitie; Life by the light uniforme in all ſoules for cariage, is the humanity; as perfect as Moyſes in the 613 Lavves; No good thing can be taught; but that is required in the Nevv Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; No ill thing can be thought, but that is reproued in the Nevv Teſtament; Ben Arama might have ſene this, and all Thalmu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diques from S. Paul 1 Tim. 1. But Eſaias ſixt, makes you as I doles, that have eies, but vvill not ſee. But you vvil be carpinge, as ſeing to much. You could not ſee Gods vviſdome in geving Zachary the name of Ieremie. And knovv you not that, to be moſt uſuall in Ezra &amp; Nehemia ſpeciallie, &amp; in Ieremie ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie; in Nechlemite, &amp; Magor-Miſſabil. And vvhy could not you carp at Barachias Mat. 23. for Iohajada. He is neuer called ſo in the old Teſtament: but you knovv the notation to be all one. Novv Zachary vvrote Chriſts his exaltation, a King riding upon an aſſe, ſold, for 30 Sicles, as a ſervant kild by an oxe, but deſtroier of Ieruſalem: after vvaters of life made to ſpring from his heauenlie Ieruſalem: vvher all thinges shalbe uſed to Gods glory; horſe bridles, as Temples veſſels. So Zacha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie hath the name Ieremie, abridging all his vvorke. And Chriſtianes had neuer taken the ſtrange vvord, but for the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious exalting of Chriſt; who did giue the ox that kild the ſeruant to the Romane butchers.</p>
               <p>But Enuie burſted your panches, vvhen you ſee all Scripture,
<pb facs="tcp:152051:44"/> &amp; all learning, contrived unto Chriſt. And thus I haue aunſwered for S. Luke; that Ieſus, Fil. Ioſeph opinione, eſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re filius Eli, &amp;c. filius Dei; and for S. Mathew, that Iechoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, the man childles, a King, neuer childleſs, begate his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ee <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or bipotentes Macedonas; parted Grecianes in the Image legges; and Moyſes clearlie ended by a ſet time for our Lordes death. And that vvhich Ben Arama moued, was handled by collaterall occaſion, that our ſymbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, or mark of faith ſpeaketh in Greke, as the Goſpell in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſpech: to go to the Father. I haue proued that by a B. D. Bil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, from Grekes abondant, that our <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> tels ſo much. And for Scriptures old, I have shevved, that vve Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtianes, know your Hebrew, better then your ſelues, for Maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoritiq exquiſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enes, for preſeruation of euerie letter. Maſſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth is a rule; and Maſſoritique: one cunning in rules that way. And your Ievves confeſs to the Princes of Germanie, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> us ye rede the pureſt Hebrevv, that vvas written ſince the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes wrote. That confeſſion should make you know, that Chiſt is God, who maketh Iaphets ſonnes his ſeruants ſo ſpeak with lippe of Chanaan. Yf you be of God, you will teach your contreyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what is aunſwered to al your objectiones: at which you ſtumbled to Gehenna hitherto; Now walk in the light of Chriſt: whom God made Heyr of all; Pſal. 2, by whom he made the world, Prov. 8: who being the brightnes of glorie, Eſa. 4. hauing the name of the Father in him, Exod. 23. by himſelf hath payd a clenſing of our ſinnes, Eſa. 4; and ſitteth on the right hand of God in the higheſt; Pſ. 110. Therfore while it is ſayd, to day, give glorie to our God, the rock Deut 32.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To the learned Nobilitie, <hi>and all other Chreſtianes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>As Iewes exceding buſied in the Prophets, ſerched all mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes to diſgrace the Goſpell, by errours of teachers unskilfull; true defenders should raquite them with groundes of Faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:44"/> that wold make them in their owne harmes Gods hated: and force them, yf they haue anie drop of grace, to bow their knee at the name of Ieſus. For this, I will heare laie downe a few ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les; with this humilitie, that yf anie can laie downe better, he yeld, upon occaſion, the better.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>1</head>
               <p>The meanes to know God, is the Word of the old Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; of the New.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>2</head>
               <p>The Ievves and vve, hold the old Teſtament, to conteine as great wiſdome, as God ſhewed in the frame of the vvorld.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>3</head>
               <p>Ther is nothing there, vvhich allureth not, unto the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of God, for ſaluation; and all of abilitie, ſhould ſpend daielie a parcell of time that vvaie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>4</head>
               <p>As the Prophecies of the old Teſtament, conteine the vviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God; ſo the Ievves should think, that the unchangea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble God being the firſt, &amp; manifeſt in Prophicie, vvold be the laſt, and shevv performance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>5</head>
               <p>The Nevv Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is in euerie reſpect, equal in vviſdome, to the old; although the Greke tongue doth not expreſs natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Philoſophie in termes fittet to matter as the Ebrevv; yet the wiſdome of God is equal in both. The old Teſtament was to shew, what wiſdome Adam once had. The Nevv Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is fittet in ſpech to the Heathen weakenes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>6</head>
               <p>In the litle book of the New teſtament, God hath ſent ſo great a varietie of pure wiſe wordes fittet from the dept of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to the preſent matter, that the language might tell God to be the auctour of the work; &amp; all are worthie of eternall flames which may ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their life in it; &amp; delite more in word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie pleaſures, then honoring God for his wiſdome to life in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:45"/>
               <head>7</head>
               <p>The ſmall N. Teſtament from fishers of Galilie, and the tet maker of Tarſus, and the Phyſician of Antiochus Magog, will call a learned reader, to the beſt Grekes through their troupes; from their firſt to the laſt; from Homer to Philemon, and Me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nander. He that knoweth Grecianes, from Homer to Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nander, ſhould find, that the little New Teſtament, will call his memorie through all. One fit for an Archbiſhoprick in En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gland, wold be commended with ſuch knowledge; &amp; the LL. of a Kinges counſell; who, by Attiq Greke, are all, Epiſcopi, and Kinges, as Antigonus for all Aſia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>8</head>
               <p>The Greke tranſlation of the old Teſtament, made by Pto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lemie Philadelphus requeſt, by 72 of Iuda, and uſed of Iewes, wher the Macedonians ſcatered them, to South, Eaſt, North, and in part to weſt, this tranſlation, is ſo skilfullie cited of Ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lilean fiſhers &amp; the reſt, that all the wittes in the world to this day, cannot folow their ſteppes, to applie their Greke unto E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brew. Diſdain not, dulnes is the cauſe of the blindnes. Biſhops of Kingdomes ſhould all be Papae, Popes of their owne ſoile; all <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Overſeers; as in the lxx; All of anie charge be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Babes be deceaved in termes. But God deliteth not in fooles. That Epiſcopus, that knoweth not what God ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the old Teſtament in Ebrew, nor what in the New in Greke is too too lerned; when he dareth teach others, that which he neuer lerned himſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>9</head>
               <p>The Apoſtles had diſputationes with the Thalmudiques; who ſpeake after the maner of the whole natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> upon the 613 Lawes of Moſes: becauſe the letters grauen by Gods writing, were 613; and the Law and Goſpel, hath no more matter, they devided all Moſes Lawes into 613. A few moo or leſſ they might have made them; but they ſaw, they fell out verie fitlie to that number. To theſe Lawes al the Apoſtles write; &amp; moſt
<pb facs="tcp:152051:45"/> upon theſe two; Iehovah, thy God, Iehovah is one: &amp;, thou ſhalt make thee a King of thy brethren. Becauſe the Eternall Sonne, who made the world, ſayd, he was the Sonne of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Atheiſt high Bishop, in Biſhop Eleazars roome, rent his clothes; as he, and all after him, deſerue to be rent with wild horſes, that after will take his place; or nevve Ievves Policie. So, becauſe he ſayd, he vvas King of the Ievves; they made this a meane to haue him King of the Heathen, and themſelves ſlaves to Ceſar. And, vpon this Lavv, Thou ſhalt reuerence my ſanctuarie; vvhen the vvord Eternall, vvho had his taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle in us, expounded moſt graciouſly hovv the Taber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacle &amp; Temple called unto him; they vvold make this, death, to ſay: Deſtroy this Tabernacle, &amp; in three dayes I vvill raiſe it vp againe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And they as he bade, deſtroyed the Tabernacle, to their eternall fall, &amp; he raiſed it up again the third day. They vvho knovv not to vvhat Lavves of Moſes theſe thinges are penned, can neuer take delite in Moſes: vvherin Kinges ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie, as David &amp; Salomon, ſhould ſpend their time, to be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes &amp; Biſhops of their people; the King able to confer Moſes vvith Ieſus, vvold be the glory of the vvorld. Novv the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtles folovving the Thalmudiq plain comon places, for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce all men, eyther to deſpiſe God in them: or to be cunning in them. And all vvho proteſt learning ſhould be aſhamed to ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve them in their librarie, &amp; not in their head. As Bodinus, vvri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting of Engliſh Lavves, vvas found vnskilful, ſo al that ſpeak of Sale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lavves, not brought vp in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vvill trip in ſpeaking of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>10</head>
               <p>A fourth kind of Greke the holie moſt vvife Apoſtles have. Termes of Athenes, applied unto voices of Salem in moſt hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>venly brightnes. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the brightnes of glorie Ebr. 1. 3. from Eſay 4. is uſed to break the revolting Rabbines. That is ſpoken of the eternall ſon our Saviour; &amp; Eſay al goeth upon that terme; &amp; Ieremie &amp; Zacharie, aliàs Ieremie, Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7, termed by notation, the exalter of Chriſt, and Zachariefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:152051:46"/> to the ſecond Elias.</p>
               <p>Very manie ſuch pearles, the Apoſtles have, vvhich I vvold handle, yf the King giue that, vvhich novv elv yere, upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvord, I looked for.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>11</head>
               <p>Manie before me, and I after others, have ſhevved, that the Thalmudiques haue ſpeches, that proue the Trinitie, vpon Eccleſiaſtes, &amp; in my two bookes in Ebrew, that, to the Grave<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Hanaw, &amp; the other to the Landgraue, I have ſhewed that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; Iewes without envy ſpeak the beſt to all the Princes of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie. S. Paul ſaith for further matter, that he differeth not from the Scribes, for the incarnation and reſurrection.</p>
               <p>Touching all that the Apoſtles have written, this muſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnderſtood; that they wrote to the ſimple of Iudah; ſpeaking moſt plainlie to their capacitie. And all their ſpeches differing from Heathen maner, are plain to all Thalmudiques; and the Apoſtles tendered the weake of the world; ſpeaking to the capa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>citie of the plaineſt: that no City but the dullard, that crucified the God of glory, wold ſay, the ſcriptures are hard; and religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is reduced to theſe principles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>Thus I have ſhevved our Lordes familie; and queſtiones de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pending therupon; &amp; I wish all that hope for life, to know firſt the familie of life. No familie in the vvorld, nor all together match it. Geve glory to our God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:152051:47"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:48"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:48"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:49"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:49"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:50"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:50"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152051:51"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:152051:51"/>
            <head>Faults Eſcaped.</head>
            <p>(*) 3. fol. lin. 7. read <hi>ſeventh moneth.</hi> and line 14. <hi>Mich.</hi> 6. 3. (*) 3. b. l. 7. <hi>sheep</hi> (*) 4. b. lin. 30. read, <hi>comment.</hi> A. 1 a. lin. 11. <hi>Addi.</hi> B. 1. b. line 20. <hi>vowels.</hi> B. 4. a. lin. 14. <hi>which was.</hi> C. 1. a. lin. 16. <hi>his tombe.</hi> And lin. 25. <hi>heavy.</hi> C. 1. b. lin. 14 <hi>perfited.</hi> and l. 25. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. C. 4. a lin. 21. <hi>lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> C. 4. b. lin. 13. <hi>ſo. muſt.</hi> D. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. a. <hi>for Math.</hi> 25. read <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 42. D. 1. b. lin. 5. <hi>Ezron.</hi> D. 3 a. lin. 19. of his <hi>name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>D. 3. b. lin. 1. <hi>infirmityes.</hi> And l. 4. <hi>infinite.</hi> And l. 15. <hi>Lev.</hi> 26. And l. 30. <hi>mourning.</hi> E. 1. a. lin. 14. <hi>whetſtone.</hi> And l. 23. <hi>Gods.</hi> E. 4. b. lin. 7. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And l. 11 <hi>cha.</hi> 38. 17. F. 1. a. lin. 12. <hi>forged.</hi> And b. lin. 22. <hi>market.</hi> And l. 32. <hi>brought.</hi> F. 4. b. lin. 5. <hi>would be.</hi> And l. 17. <hi>knees.</hi> G. 1. a. lin. 3. <hi>yee that</hi> And l. 18. <hi>the common.</hi> And l. 22. <hi>citeth.</hi> G. 1. b. lin. 7. <hi>who was.</hi> And l. 10. <hi>webb.</hi> And l. 11 <hi>grieved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And l. 15. <hi>no kin to him.</hi> G. 2. b. l. 28. <hi>images.</hi> And l. 29. <hi>Trinacria.</hi> And l. 30. <hi>vnder one mount.</hi> H. 2. b. lin. 20. <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth.</hi> And l. 27. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. H. 3. b. lin. 26. <hi>Rodanim. Riphath.</hi> I. 1. b. lin. 29. <hi>Caari.</hi> And 2. a. lin. 22, <hi>Magor-miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabib.</hi> And, b, lin, 19, <hi>is God.</hi> And l, 33, <hi>requite.</hi> I, 3. a, lin, 24, 27, 30. <hi>fitted,</hi> And l, 30, <hi>depth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>In the Greek.</head>
            <p>K, fol, 4. lin, 18, read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
